<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Happiness at hand. Or A plain and practical discourse of the joy of just mens souls in the state of separation from the body. For the instruction of weak Christians, and for the comfort of the afflicated. / By J. B. Rector of Finchamsted in the county of Berks.</title>
            <author>Brandon, John, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53298971</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53298971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2801:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Happiness at hand. Or A plain and practical discourse of the joy of just mens souls in the state of separation from the body. For the instruction of weak Christians, and for the comfort of the afflicated. / By J. B. Rector of Finchamsted in the county of Berks.</title>
                  <author>Brandon, John, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 191, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for L. Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, July 2. 1686."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement and errata, p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ascension of the soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Happineſs at Hand.</hi> OR A Plain and Practical DISCOURSE OF THE Joy of Juſt Mens Souls in the State of Separation from the Body. For the Inſtruction of Weak Chriſtians, and for the Comfort of the Afflicted. By <hi>J. B.</hi> Rector of <hi>Finchamſted</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 63.3.</hi>
               </bibl> Thy Loving Kindneſs is better than Life.</q>
            <q>Qui cupit diſſolvi, &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto, haud patienter moritur, ſed patienter vivit, &amp; delectabiliter moritur.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>LICENSED,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 2. 1686.</date>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>L. Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:3"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory. <hi>To the Worſhipfull, and my moſt worthily honoured Friend,</hi> Dr. Robert Woodward, <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of my Lord Biſhop's Court at</hi> Sarum.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I have adventured to make uſe of your Name in this way, ſo I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, 'tis ſcarce more eaſie for uncharitable Minds to <hi>Blame</hi> me for it, than for your <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Courteſie</hi> to excuſe it,
<pb facs="tcp:179751:4"/>in ſome Meaſure; And if Any ſhould account me preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſo doing, I can truly tell them, That I had a very great, (and almoſt Irreſiſtible) <hi>Temptation</hi> to it: For, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of good Repute and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do not ſeem to doubt, but I might bear the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> as well as <hi>Imprudence;</hi> if, (having an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity) I ſhould not make ſome publick <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> of my <hi>Obligations</hi> to your <hi>Worſhip,</hi> for thoſe great Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your undeſerved <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> which (Bleſſed be God) I ſo happily received, in thoſe publick <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> that made me ſtand in need of ſo <hi>Good</hi> a <hi>Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:4"/>
            <p>Accept therefore, I beſeech you, Sir, this plain <hi>Piece,</hi> as a <hi>Pledge</hi> of the unfeigned <hi>Thanks</hi> that I muſt <hi>ever</hi> owe you.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, I do the rather beg your <hi>Acceptance</hi> of it, becauſe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> defended is apparently owned by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and, partly, Becauſe if it find (in the Main) that <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Favour,</hi> I ſhall think my ſelf ſufficiently Armed againſt the <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the <hi>Profane, Malignant World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Mercies</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you ſtill with His <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> Granting you many <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Days</hi> here on Earth; and, when your <hi>Time</hi> is ended;
<pb facs="tcp:179751:5"/>the <hi>Joys</hi> of <hi>Eternity,</hi> and the <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of Them that <hi>Dye</hi> in the Lord. So praying, refteth, (Good Sir)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhip's, moſt humble Servant, and moſt effectually obliged,</hi>John Brandon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:5"/>
            <head>A Word to the READER.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader. If thou askeſt, why I publiſh this Diſcourſe? I can ſafely anſwer, 'Tis not to offend thee. But poſſibly Thou mayſt expect ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Account, which take as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The Subject here treated of, is not ſo commonly handled as many other Points of Religion; Among the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Books abroad in the World (which I have made ſome Enquiry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) there is not ſo much as one Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Volume, that I can find, written upon it, purpoſely, plainly and practically; And Thoſe that have ſpoken occaſionally of it in larger Pieces containing various Subjects, have ſaid a great deal more than they have proved, about it; I could ſhew a prety many pages relating to it, that afford not ſo much as one good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial
<pb facs="tcp:179751:6"/>Argument for the truth of it; and yet it deſerveth to be as well proved as moſt Doctrines that I know of, (and much better than ſome that have been ſufficiently contended for.)</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> 'Tis a Subject that ſeems to afford an Eminent Degree of Support and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to a Pious Soul. For though the Being <hi>(for ever with the Lord)</hi> be the Top of our Felicity, (whether we enjoy it ſooner or later) yet, me thinks the Hope of being with Him in a little Time may be agreat Addition to a Chriſtian's Joy.</p>
            <p>May it not be a Matter of Special (yea ſtrong) Conſolation, to think and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (on Scripture grounds) that he ſhall be a Gainer by his Diſſolution, have his Soul with Chriſt and his Angels before his Body is with Worms, and Duſt, and ſee the Eternal Light and Love, as ſoon as Death has drawn the Vail of Fleſh?</p>
            <p>And that it may Aſſiſt thee (Chriſtian Reader) in the chearfull Service of thy God, (which is the trueſt Heaven that Thou canſt hope for here on Earth) is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:179751:6"/>evident that it need not be proved. Well may he ſerve his God with Gladneſs, that hopeth ſo ſhortly to ſee his Salvation.</p>
            <p>And I was the more encouraged to go on herein, becauſe I feared no Oppoſers: For the Church of <hi>England</hi> teacheth its Friends to ſay (in the Burial Service) <hi>[O God with whom the Souls of the Faithfull, after they are delivered from the Fleſh, are in Joy and Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.]</hi> And if I am oppoſed by its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, it will be matter of ſmall Regard with me, (yet if any man of what perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoever, ſhall employ his Pen to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Main of what I have ſaid on this Point, He may be attended to, if God grant Life and Leiſure.)</p>
            <p>I can eaſily judge, that a Work of this Nature were fitter to be managed by others, than by Me, yet that muſt not hinder me from doing it, as I can. And if my Imperfect Doing of it may Anger any man ſo far as to move him to do it Better, I ſhall think, I have written to very good purpoſe.
<pb facs="tcp:179751:7"/>And now, I have onely to Requeſt of thee theſe few things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That thou wouldſt reade over this Diſcourſe (when thou haſt not a better at hand,) for which I need urge no other Motives, than the Smallneſs of it, and the Greatneſs of it's Subject.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That thou reade it with a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Eye, and a Chriſtian Aim, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Truth with all Readineſs of mind; not Rejecting any thing thou findeſt to be Sound, for the Sake of any thing that thou thinkeſt to be weak.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That thou wouldſt beſeech God of all Grace, to give us ſuch Grace as may be ſufficient for us; ſuch as may fit us both (in his due time) for the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of that Felicity which this ſmall Book is deſigned to Diſcover. I add no more but to Subſcribe my Self</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Servant, for the Sake of Jeſus,</hi> John Brandon</signed>
               <dateline>Fincham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted (Berks) <date>May 10th. <hi>1686.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:7"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents of this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE Introduction, with ſome Preſuppoſitions relating to the Point,</hi> (Viz.) <hi>The Soul's Immortality, and it's Capableneſs of being Happy out of the Body.</hi> Page 1</item>
               <item>SECTION I. <hi>The Happineſs of good Mens Souls in their Separation from the Body aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and the Probability of it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</hi> pag. 12</item>
               <item>SECT. II. <hi>The happy State of good Mens Souls after Death, proved from</hi> Phil. 1.23. <hi>[having a Deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better,] to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with an Anſwer to a Socinian Exception.</hi> pag. 17</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:179751:8"/>
               <item>SECT. III. <hi>The Point proved from</hi> Luke 23.43. [<hi>This day Thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe, and</hi> Coloſ. 1.20. <hi>To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile all things to himſelf, whether Things on Earth, or Things in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven] with an Anſwer to ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</hi> pag. 26</item>
               <item>SECT. IV. <hi>The ſame proved from</hi> 2 Cor. 5.8. <hi>[We are willing rather to be abſent from the Body, and preſent with the Lord,] and</hi> Heb. 12.23. <hi>[The Spirits of Juſt Men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.]</hi> pag. 31</item>
               <item>SECT. V. <hi>The ſame Doctrine proved from</hi> Rev. 14.13. [<hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their Labours,</hi> &amp;c.] pag. 36</item>
               <item>SECT. VI. <hi>The happineſs of Juſt Mens Souls, in the State of Separation vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> pag. 39</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:179751:8"/>
               <item>SECT. VII. <hi>The Point improved, for Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Errors.</hi> pag. 45</item>
               <item>SECT. VIII.<hi>For trial of our ſelves, whether we are of the number of thoſe Juſt ones, that may juſtly expect this approaching Felicity.</hi> pag. 48
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An Appendix to the Eighth Section, being a Character of that Juſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe Soul ſhall ſhortly be ſo happy.</hi> pag. 71</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. IX. <hi>Shewing the Uſefulneſs of the Point, in two other Particulars.</hi> pag. 83.</item>
               <item>SECT. X. <hi>Being a Perſwaſive to ſeveral great Duties.</hi> pag. 88</item>
               <item>SECT. XI. <hi>Containing the Reſolution of two great Queſtions.</hi> pag. 95</item>
               <item>SECT. XII. <hi>Treating of the Nature of this
<pb facs="tcp:179751:9"/>Happineſs, and the Joy that attends it.</hi> pag. 113</item>
               <item>SECT. XIII. <hi>Shewing the Greatneſs of the Love of Chriſt, which the Souls of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all enjoy after Death.</hi> pag. 132</item>
               <item>SECT. XIV. <hi>Diſcovering the Greatneſs of Chriſt's Love, in what he did or ſuffered for Sinners.</hi> pag. 142</item>
               <item>SECT. XV. <hi>Being other brief Improvements of the Point.</hi> page. 150.</item>
               <item>SECT. XVI. <hi>Being a farther Improvement of the Doctrine aforeſaid, as an Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Fear of Death.</hi> pag. 157</item>
               <item>A POSTSCRIPT. <hi>Attempting the Reſolution of a Weighty Queſtion, with an Appendix to the</hi> 13th. <hi>Section, concerning Chriſt's Filiation; in a Letter to a learned Authour.</hi> pag. 185</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179751:9"/>
            <head>Happineſs at Hand.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction, with ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſitions relating to the Point.</head>
               <p>THAT Godlineſs is great gain, and the ways there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of peace and pleaſantneſs, is aſſured to us by the Authour of that bleſſed Book which may ſave our Souls but cannot deceive them. And though Religion be ſo good in this Life that every good action may afford ſome degree of comfort (as Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi> was wont to ſay) when the Soul is not under temptations and miſtakes; yet the beſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is reſerved for another World,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179751:10"/>and its ſtrongeſt Conſolations kept in ſtore to be enjoyed in that high and holy place where there is joy without ſorrow, peace without trouble, Sanctification without Sin, and all without end.</p>
               <p>And that thy Joy may be full, conſider (Chriſtian Reader) what grounds thou haſt to believe that this Happineſs is at Hand alſo, and ſhall be poſſeſſed in good part by thy Soul in its ſeparated State; moſt certainly the love of thy Lord is better than Life, and will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thy Spirit than the life of thy Fleſh and all the comforts of this lower World; the diſcovery of which I am not preſently to attempt, but rather to premiſe a few particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in order to it.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing to be ſuppoſed as the Foundation of what follows, is <hi>[The immortality of Mens Souls]</hi> which ſome have been ſo brutiſh as to call in queſtion imagining that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179751:10"/>Men die (in all reſpects) as the Beaſts that periſh and therefore live as if Body and Soul ſhould rot together.</p>
               <p>Whoſe folly therein I need, on this occaſion, no farther to ſhew than by conſidering the words of him who is the faithfull and true Witneſs, and knows us better than we do our ſelves, <hi>viz. Mat.</hi> 10.28. <hi>[Fear not them that can kill the Body, but are not able to kill the Soul.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words our Saviour ſpake plain enough: nor can any ſubtilty in the earth evade the force of them; or obſcure to any purpoſe, the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Teſtimony which they give to the Souls Immortality. For they are brought in as an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel; an incouragement I ſay, againſt the fury of Perſecutours (of whom he ſpake in the foregoing verſes.) He would not have this diſhearten them: <hi>Fear not</hi> (ſays he)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179751:11"/>
                  <hi>them that can kill the Body but are not able to kill the Soul. q. d.</hi> [As they can do nothing more againſt you than they are permitted to doe, ſo the worſt they can poſſibly do to you can kill no more than your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: your nobler parts your Souls are above the reach of all their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; therefore fear them not in any diſcouraging way.] Will not any one that readeth that Text with heedfulneſs, and without prejudice, be ſatisfied that this is the meaning of it? And if it were deſigned by our Saviour to expreſs the Souls im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, how could it be done more effectually and more plainly in a few words? But nothing is plain enough to them that will not ſee the truth. The ſtrength of which as to this particular, may appear by the weakneſs of thoſe Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the contrary minded have put upon this Text.</p>
               <p n="1">1. (Say ſome) the killing of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179751:11"/>Soul may be meant of <hi>Damning</hi> it. They cannot <hi>kill</hi> it with Eternal <hi>Death</hi> or Damnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That none of the greateſt Perſecutours could kill the Soul in <hi>that manner</hi> is very true, but 'tis not the meaning of that Text [<hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.] For the Damning of the Soul is not ſpoken of in the word, <hi>kill;</hi> but in the word, <hi>Deſtroying;</hi> but fear him who is able to <hi>Deſtroy</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul in Hell, (in the ſame verſe) now to <hi>[kill,]</hi> and to <hi>[Deſtroy,]</hi> are different words, and as different things: the diſobedient are threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an everlaſting <hi>[Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,]</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. but no where with an everlaſting <hi>killing.</hi> 2. The <hi>[killing]</hi> of the Soul which is there denied to be in the power of Men, is not to be underſtood of <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe <hi>that</hi> is never expreſſed by that word (in Scripture) Let any Man ſhew ſo much as one Text therein where the <hi>Damnation</hi> either
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179751:12"/>of the Soul or of the Perſon is called a <hi>killing</hi> of the one or the other. 3. The ſame word in the Original is uſed of both, which ſhews it meant in the ſame ſenſe of both. So that as the word <hi>[everlaſting]</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46.) ſpoken of the puniſhment of the wicked, is the ſame that is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Life, or Glory, of the Righteous; and therefore proves the perpetuity of the former as well as of the latter, as is ſhewed elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.) So the Original word for <hi>[killing]</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Everlaſting Fire no Fancy.</hi> Cap. 1. Sect. 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] being the ſame for ſubſtance that is uſed in the ſaid Text, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>killing</hi> of the Soul and of the Body, it muſt needs be underſtood accordingly.</p>
               <p>So that [they can kill the Body but cannot kill the Soul] muſt needs ſignifie to us that the Soul continues to live the life of a Soul when the Body ceaſeth to live the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179751:12"/>life of a Body. And I know not how any can deny it unleſs he be reſolved upon perverſeneſs, and will offer violence to the plaineſt ſpeeches imaginable.</p>
               <p n="4">4. At that rate of Interpretation which theſe Objectors uſe, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhould, (therein) have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no more of the Soul than may be ſaid of the Body. For Men (we know) cannot <hi>Damn</hi> the Body no more than the Soul. But there we ſee the <hi>[killing]</hi> which is denied as to the Soul, is granted of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy [<hi>that can,</hi> ſays our Lord, <hi>kill the Body but cannot kill the Soul.</hi>] And if any yet think the meaning is that no Perſecutors can damn the Souls of God's Servants, I wou'd fain know why they ſuppoſe him to have taught ſo plain a truth in ſo dark a manner; For how ſhall we be certain that <hi>[killing]</hi> means <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in that place, when it ſignifieth no ſuch thing in any other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:179751:13"/>
               <p>Others can fancy the meaning is [that men cannot <hi>kill</hi> the Soul for ever] or for good and all (as we ſay.) But that's as vain as the former, and appears to be ſo by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for then there ſhould be no more ſaid of the Soul than may be ſaid of the Body; for they cannot kill the Body for ever: it ſhall be alive after death has done its worſt; <hi>It ſhall be raiſed Incorruptible</hi> (1 Cor. 15.) <hi>and this mortal muſt put on Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that the word, <hi>kill,</hi> (in St. <hi>Matthew</hi>) muſt be meant of killing <hi>[for ever]</hi> no proof can be pretended to either from the phraſe, or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, or ſcope of the place, and therefore it might be ſufficient to deny it without confuting it.</p>
               <p>Others again would evade the force of this Text of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> by comparing it with <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Fear not them that kill the Body, but after that have no more that they can
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179751:13"/>do,</hi> where there is nothing ſaid of the Impoſſibility of killing the Soul. —And indeed as a Kingdom is moſt in danger when it is divided againſt it ſelf, ſo Religion (they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) is moſt powerfully reſiſted when it is oppoſed by its own ſtrength, (by that bleſſed word which is at once its rule and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) But it cannot be uſed for ſo ill a purpoſe without groſs ignorance or great perverſneſs as may eaſily be exemplified in the ſaid Objection.</p>
               <p>For (firſt) both theſe Texts are from the ſame Spirit of Truth: and however the latter be expreſſed, yet the former is the word of Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and he really meaneth as he ſpeaketh therein. And if Men could any way make the Soul of Man to <hi>ceaſe</hi> to be a living Soul, it would ſignifie little to ſay that they cannot <hi>kill</hi> it; ſince (on that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal) they may do as much, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be properly called killing or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179751:14"/>no: nor would that Man well eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the imputation of a Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer that ſhould ſay the infinite wiſedom would ſpeak ſo vainly on any occaſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But yet St. <hi>Luke</hi> doth not ſo expreſs it, and St. <hi>Matthew</hi> (ſay ſome) may be expounded by S. <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Though it be not ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by St. <hi>Luke,</hi> yet where it is ſo expreſſed, I deſire the liberty of believing it true. 2. There is no neceſſity (in this affair) of expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the one by the other; and if there were it may ſeem fitter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.4. by <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. than contrarily, for that of <hi>Matthew</hi> is more ſpecial and particular than that of <hi>Luke.</hi> And if any will ſay our Saviour did not intend to teach us the Souls immortality in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, becauſe he did not mention it in the latter, yet we muſt not ſuffer their confidence to carry it, (as we ſay) or take their word for it. Nor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179751:14"/>can they require us ſo to doe unleſs they ſhould pretend to Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s profoundneſs, or a greater Man's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility.</p>
               <p>Having ſuppoſed, and in part proved, that the Soul of Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains alive after his Body is dead; the next particular I would premiſe is this [that it is a Subject capable of joy or ſorrow after it leaves the Body] according as it leaveth it in a State of Sin or a State of Grace. It is not like ſome ſort of Inſects in the depth of Winter, that have a vital principle without motion or operation, that are alive and ſeem as inſenſible as if they were dead.</p>
               <p>I know ſome would perſwade us the Soul ſleeps after Death: but their great errors in other things may fully excuſe us from believing them in this; and I think it as ſtrange a fancy as can enter into the Head of any Man that hath his underſtanding well awake: for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179751:15"/>as the Pſalmiſt ſays of God <hi>[He that made the Eye ſhall he not ſee?]</hi> So we may ſay of the Soul, that which gives ſenſe to the Body, ſhall not it perceive? eſpecially ſince it liveth after it leaves the Body (as hath been proved.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The Happineſs of good Mens Souls, in their Separation from the Body aſſerted, and the probability of it diſcovered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore the proof and Vindication of this point it may be proper to ſhew the probability of it (that they who are not perſwaded 'tis true may not be over confident that it is falſe) by ſhewing the judgment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179751:15"/>of Eminent Writers, that are preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med able to judge of a matter of this nature. And if I were to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a Romaniſt of it I might cite the noted Men of his Church. <hi>i.e.</hi> (1.) <hi>Aquin.</hi> their great Schoolman <hi>Sum. prim.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">dae.</hi> 
                  <hi>queſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Art.</hi> 5. <hi>Aliqui dicunt quod Animae ſeparatae ad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudinem non perveniunt,</hi> &amp;c. <q rend="inline">Some (ſays he) tell us that good Mens Souls come not to Bleſſedneſs till the day of Judgment.</q> But this is plainly falſe. In like manner goes <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his tract <hi>de Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Moriendi,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>Lib. de aſcenſ. mentis grad.</hi> 2 <hi>chap.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>Quid mirum (ait) ſi Angeli &amp; beatae Animae,</hi> &amp;c. Where he joins toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Angels and Juſt Mens Souls, doubting the happineſs of the one no more than the other. So <hi>grad.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. — <hi>Quibus perpetuus Dies eſt,</hi> &amp;c. [Speaking of the ſame] 'Tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways day with them, they know no darkneſs of ſin or ſorrow. <hi>Tho. à
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179751:16"/>Kempis de imitat. Chriſti lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>Drexel. Heliotrop. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Cajetan in Philip.</hi> 1.23. moſt plainly, in ſeveral paſſages that I need not tranſcribe. But I leave theſe and rather cite our Proteſtant Worthies. <hi>Muſculus in Math.</hi> 17. <hi>Mors piorum Egreſſus eſt ex mundo ad patrem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> The death of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones is a going out of this World to their Heavenly Father, therefore to be deſired more than to be drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>Zanchius in Philip</hi> 1.23. <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſui parte,</hi> &amp;c. — [In what reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect did <hi>Paul</hi> deſire after his diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be with <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Not in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of his Body, apparently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of his <hi>Soul:</hi> therefore his Soul was capable of that Happineſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after death.] Others ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe as follows, <hi>D. Joh. Maccov. de Anim. fept in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plic. Theorem.</hi> 2. <hi>Urſin. Catech. part.</hi> 2. <hi>Reſp. ad queſt.</hi> 42. <hi>Paraeus in Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Reſp. ad Dub.</hi> 9. <hi>Alſted. Theol. Caſuum
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179751:16"/>p.</hi> 172. <hi>Piſcator in Philip.</hi> 1. <hi>Eſſenius in Triumpho Crucis (de ſatisf Chriſti) lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 3 (<hi>part.</hi> 1.) <hi>Dan. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miet. lib.</hi> 25. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>(de Beatitudine) Joſ. Stegman. Photin. diſp.</hi> 52. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Jo. Scarpii curſ. theol. de purgatorio. Palan. ſyntagmo l.</hi> 7 <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Arnoldus</hi> (<hi>Lux. in Tenebr. p.</hi> 418. <hi>D. Henr. Altin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius L. C. Loc.</hi> 5. <hi>Controverſ.</hi> 2. — To whom I may add a few of our Engliſh Worthies (and thoſe are as good as a great many) Bp. <hi>Uſher ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſtian Religion</hi> (of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) Bp. <hi>Prideaux Faſcicul. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ q.</hi> 2. B. <hi>Davenant</hi> in <hi>Coloſ. cap. 8. ver.</hi> 15. <hi>Bolton de</hi> 4. <hi>Noviſſimis.</hi> And this at leaſt muſt be a probable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the truth of what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for: for that is like to be ſound Doctrine which is ſo evidently own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe excellent Authors ſo bleſſedly enriched with the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from above. And if any ſuch, (or leſs than they) had written a ſet Diſcourſe on it, plainly and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179751:17"/>and to the capacities of vulgar Chriſtians, I might have ſpared the little pains that I have taken about it.</p>
               <p>If then I have erred in maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Principle I have erred with Company (and good Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny too) But I truſt the enſuing Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will ſhew it to be a truth to thoſe that ſeek the truth in love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179751:17"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The Happy State of Good Mens Souls after death proved from</hi> Philip. 1.23. <hi>[having a deſire to depart and to be with Chriſt, which is far better] together with an Anſwer to a Socinian exception.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving told thee (Chriſtian Reader) that this Doctrine is probably true, I am now to ſhew how certainly 'tis ſo, and that in the firſt place from thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>[Having a deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.]</hi> In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. he called Death an Enemy, and doubtleſs he was not in love with it as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in itſelf: But yet to die and be with Chriſt, this he heartily deſired
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179751:18"/>as that which would be far better for him. He tells his beloved Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (<hi>verſ.</hi> 24.) that his continuance in the World would be moſt for their benefit. <hi>[To abide in the Fleſh, is more needfull for you.]</hi> But his <hi>departing</hi> would be moſt for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit being a <hi>departing</hi> and being with Chriſt. And therefore he was in a ſtrait (as he calls it) not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which to chuſe. Now if he ſhould not upon his departure be with Chriſt, as to his Soul, he muſt needs have accounted a longer life to be moſt deſireable. For as to others good it was apparently ſo, and no leſs for his own good alſo, if his Soul could have no happineſs in its ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from the Body; for he had a great degree of comfort in Chriſt while he was living, and could ſay in the midſt of all his Perſecutions, Bleſſed be God who always giveth us cauſe to Triumph in Chriſt. And he that had an eminent meaſure of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179751:18"/>Communion with Chriſt while li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and all thoſe ſtrong Conſolations that flowed from his aſſurance that nothing ſhould ſeparate from his love (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) would have been a great loſer by dying, if his Soul muſt then have been deprived of thoſe precious comforts which before he had in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely St. <hi>Paul's</hi> words ſhew no fear of any ſuch thing, but plainly evince the contrary, as the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in other caſes would be thought to import. Suppoſe one ſay, [I deſire to go to <hi>London</hi> and ſee my Friends, or, I deſire to go to Church and profit my Soul] In theſe ſpeeches any Man of reaſon would judge (unleſs the perſon had the reputation of a Lyar) that he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly meant as he ſpake, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to ſee his Friends by doing the one, and to benefit his Soul in doing the other. And ſo in Scripture, <hi>To go up and ſee the Land, to go over and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179751:19"/>poſſeſs it</hi> (<hi>Numb.</hi> 13.30. <hi>Deut</hi> 3.25.) are meant of going to ſee and poſſeſs it as the Way to the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s phraſe <hi>[to depart and be with Chriſt]</hi> were not meant in like manner, it were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than very ſtrange; and it can be no otherwiſe, his being <hi>with Chriſt</hi> after his departure being affirmed to be a better ſtate than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had (notwithſtanding the enjoyments before mentioned) nor muſt our Oppoſers right reaſon (which they talk ſo much of) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us from expounding the words in that way that is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to common ſenſe.</p>
               <p>And though this may ſeem plain enough to any unprejudiced perſon, yet it will not be amiſs to anſwer what is excepted againſt it, and to clear it from that darkneſs which ſome have (ſo learnedly) caſt upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> And as to this I know none more conſiderable than <hi>V. Smalcius,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179751:19"/>who in his Diſputation <hi>[De Judicio Extremo]</hi> is pleaſed to preſent us with this <hi>Memorandum, viz.</hi> 1. That St. <hi>Paul</hi> there makes no mention of his Soul, but ſpeaketh <hi>[De ſe toto]</hi> of his whole Perſon. 2. That he might die and be with Chriſt at the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time (the Reſurrection) without <hi>ſuppoſing any Being with Chriſt preſently after death.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By this Man's temper (and Tenet) we may ſee that humane Learning and Acuteneſs is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make a Man ſound in the Faith, and it might move our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that one of ſo much ſubtilty ſhould not perceive the Apoſtles meaning in this particular, if we did not remember the old ſaying, <hi>None ſo blind as thoſe that will not ſee,</hi> for had it been (confeſſedly) inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſhew his Souls being with Chriſt (or enjoying of him) upon his <hi>departure,</hi> yet it needed not have been expreſſed otherwiſe than by a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179751:20"/>deſire to depart and be with Chriſt. For after his departure he could not be with Chriſt as to his Body till the Reſurrection; which will be at the time appointed and cannot be haſtened by his (or any Man's) ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Life. Nor could he deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this Life, if it were not for the hope of being with Chriſt in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate thereby, ſince it was more for his Peoples profit to have lived longer with them. And we are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied he was not weary of his Life through the troubles that he met with in the ſervice of Chriſt (his Faith and Love was more powerfull than ſo) nor doth he name any thing but his being with Chriſt (which was far better) as a motive to him to deſire to depart this Life.</p>
               <p>And to ſay ['tis not meant of his Soul's being with Chriſt, becauſe he ſpeaks of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his <hi>Soul</hi>] is indeed to talk more like an Ignorant Man than a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179751:20"/>or a Diſputant, for 'tis ſpoken of his <hi>Perſon</hi> in reſpect of his <hi>Soul:</hi> and nothing is more common in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe than to ſpeak that of Perſons, which holds true of them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Bodies, or their Souls (though not both perhaps) as when we ſay, they are Sick or Lame, Wiſe and Knowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we hope we may ſpeak true enough, and proper enough too, though we do not ſay <hi>(formaliter)</hi> they are Sick as to their Bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] but ſay (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely) [they are ſick] ſo when Scripture ſays, <hi>To duſt thou ſhalt return,</hi> it muſt be taken accordingly: and my Authors Brain was not ſo Earthy as to think it muſt be ſo therefore with his whole Perſon; or to argue that Man's Soul ſhall turn to Duſt, becauſe 'tis ſaid <hi>to Duſt [thou] ſhalt return.</hi> More therefore I need not ſay upon this Argument, till others think fit to ſay more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Yet for the comfort of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179751:21"/>weak Chriſtians I think fit to add, that this privilege [of being with Chriſt after Death] is not peculiar to St. <hi>Paul</hi> but belongs alſo to all that are truly Godly. Death (as well as Life) is <hi>yours,</hi> ſaid he to the believing <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and in them to all other faithfull Chriſtians, and certainly he meant, t'was theirs in a comfortable ſenſe, for their good, and leading to their happineſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. And if all things work for good to them that love God, Death ſhall alſo (and do <hi>them</hi> a kindneſs as well as the Apoſtle) <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. nor doth the Apoſtle make any compariſon between himſelf and the reſt of the faithfull in this caſe, or ſet himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them in any reſpect: as alſo in other places he declares them to have the ſame intereſt in him, and Acceptance for his ſake. <hi>Chriſt who is our Life,</hi> Coloſ. 34. <hi>He made us accepted in the Beloved,</hi> Eph. 1.6. Phil. 4.19. <hi>[My God ſhall ſupply all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179751:21"/>your need according to his Riches in Glory through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Yea, <hi>He is made unto us, Wiſedom and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and Sanctification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30.</p>
               <p>And that the Souls of other Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians are capable of happineſs after death, as well as S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove when I can think worth while ſo to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:179751:22"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The point proved from</hi> Luke 23.43. <hi>[This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe; and</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ. 1.20. <hi>To reconcile all things to himſelf whether things on Earth or things in Heaven] with an Anſwer to ſome exceptions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMong the many Scriptures that confirm this comfortable Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, theſe are very conſiderable. In the former our Saviour tells the dying Penitent the joyfull News <hi>[This day thou ſhalt be with me in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe]</hi> but he was not ſo in reſpect of his Body, therefore in reſpect of his Soul. Whether his Soul was to be that day in Heaven, or only ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it, I ſhall not here enquire;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179751:22"/>'Tis enough for my purpoſe that it was to be in <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> for that can ſignifie no leſs than a place and ſtate of happineſs. And we doubt not but Chriſt's favourable preſence could make any place a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> for delight, and more delightfull than the Earthly <hi>Paradiſe</hi> ever was. This Text is ſo ſtrong on our ſide that our greateſt oppoſers can hardly tell what to ſay to it, any otherwiſe than by eſpouſing that wretched e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of the foreſaid <hi>Racovian</hi> Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Val. Smalcius,</hi> viz. Changing the Sentence, by miſplacing the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, and reading the words thus <hi>[Verily I ſay to thee this day, Thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe]</hi> namely, ſome time or other, as if <hi>[this day] were meant of Chriſt's ſpeaking, and not of the Penitent's enjoying. Modus loquendi Hebraicus,</hi> &amp;c. It is, ſays he, <hi>a ſpeaking after the manner of the Hebrews,</hi> who uſe to expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo, when they would tell us
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179751:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:179751:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:179751:24"/>matters of ſpecial remark, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.18. <hi>If ye Worſhip other Gods and ſerve them, I denounce unto you this day that ye ſhall ſurely periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if they gain the cauſe at ſuch a rate,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.43. <hi>cleared.</hi>
                  </note> let them take all, and ſet up their own Hereſie for ſacred and ſaying truths. For 'tis eaſie to turn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th into errour, and ſenſe into non-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, by miſ-pointing any places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or any other Books; and when Men make ſo bold with the words of our Lord, we may fitly call them to account for it, and cenſure their preſumption and perverſeneſs, which in this caſe ſeems very plain. For firſt, they ſhew us no good reaſon why it ſhould be read <hi>[I ſay unto thee this day]</hi> nor was there need that Chriſt ſhould tell him that he ſaid ſo in <hi>that day;</hi> nor do we find him uſe ſuch an expreſſion in any place, or on any great occaſions.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179751:24"/>For when he would tell us the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Converſion, he ſays not [<hi>I ſay unto you this day,</hi> but [<hi>Verily I ſay unto you, except ye be converted ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and the like of his being own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Angels [<hi>Verily, Verily I ſay unto you, hereafter ye ſhall ſee Heaven open, and the Angels of God aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and deſcending upon the Son of Man,</hi> Joh 1.51.</p>
               <p>Vain enough therefore is that Author's ſuggeſtion, that it was ſo ſpoken for the weightineſs of the matter. And though in the Old Teſtament there were ſuch phraſes uſed <hi>[I ſay to thee this day]</hi> yet it was in matters of threat, or of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but not in matters of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or comfort. Our Lord alſo hath it [<hi>Verily I ſay,</hi> &amp;c.] now as there was no need at all of <hi>ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn</hi> Aſſeveration to tell the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Thief <hi>when</hi> it was he ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him (his own Ears being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179751:25"/>ſo it was very <hi>proper</hi> to be uſed in telling him of the happy change that he ſhould make ſo <hi>ſpeedily,</hi> and tended much to ſatisfie him in it.</p>
               <p>So that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.20. <hi>to reconcile all things to himſelf, whether things on Earth or things in Heaven.</hi> Here what can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe meant by <hi>[things in Heaven re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled] Piſcator</hi> expoundeth <hi>tam fideles,</hi> &amp;c. as well the faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to Heaven as thoſe ſtill on Earth. If this be the ſenſe of it 'tis full enough to prove the faithfull Chriſtians Soul to be happy after death: and if it be not, I almoſt deſpair of knowing it. As to the Holy Angels it ſeems very improper to interpret it of them; for how are they Things reconciled that never offended their God, and ſo needed not any reconciliation? [And there is in that Chapter no diſcourſe of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> or any thing to enforce it to be meant of them and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179751:25"/>whether the expreſſing it by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all things, not [all Perſons] he may not have a ſpecial reſpect to the Souls of the faithfull departed, I leave to others to conſider of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The ſame proved from</hi> 2 Cor. 5.8. [<hi>we are willing rather to be abſent from the Body, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord; and</hi> Heb. 12.23. <hi>[The Spirits of juſt Men made perfect.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF other places ſhould not ſatisfie Men as to this particular, yet <hi>theſe</hi> one would think could not fail of ſo doing. In the former St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks nothing that was peculiar to himſelf, but joyneth the reſt of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179751:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfull in the very ſame privilege with himſelf. [We, ſays he, are willing to be abſent from the Body, and to be preſent with the Lord.] Wherefore it muſt needs be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Apoſtle did believe that when they were (as he calls it) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Body, they ſhould be preſent with the Lord, not only in a general ſenſe, as all things are, but in a <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> manner, and ſuch as containeth more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Communion with him than any they could have in this mortal Life; and that their <hi>being thus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them, when abſent from the Body is to be underſtood in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Souls, is that which needeth not to be proved to any that make uſe of ſober reaſon, and are willing to underſtand the plaineſt words; and I find not that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded have made any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt this proof that are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy any ſerious conſideration. And
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179751:26"/>for that of the Apoſtle, [<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23] I take it to be no leſs convincing; <hi>For what but the Souls of good Men can be ſuppoſed to be called the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect?</hi> For it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid of the Angels, they being diſtinguiſhed from them in the ſame verſe, nor can it be meant of the Perſons of Men (Bodies and Souls united) for theſe are called Men, and not Spirits; much leſs the Spirits of juſt Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But we find in Scripture, the Angels that have a charge over the faithfull are called <hi>their</hi> Angels, and why may they not be called <hi>their</hi> Spirits, being Spirits indeed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The queſtion in this matter is not, whether they <hi>may</hi> not be ſo called in ſome ſenſe, or reſpect? but whether in that Text they <hi>are</hi> ſo called, and I ſay they are not, for two Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Angels are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned juſt before (as was intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179751:27"/>and they are never called the Spirits of Men, or the Spirits of the Juſt, in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe theſe are ſpoken of as made perfect (as the things that are imperfect are brought to perfection by degrees, for ſo the original ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth) now the Holy Angels never were deſtitute of any perfection that their nature needeth. Since therefore it muſt be only the Souls of the Juſt that there are called the Spirits of the Juſt, it will be eaſie to conclude the point from it. For 'tis evident it cannot be meant of their Spirits (or Souls) while in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy here on Earth; for in this ſtate they are not made perfect, but have a great deal of ſinfull imperfection in them: not as though I were <hi>alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perfect,</hi> ſaid St. <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf. <hi>And 'tis ſaid they are made perfect:</hi> that is, <hi>already perfect;</hi> and therefore is not ſpoken of that perfection which they ſhall have <hi>hereafter at
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179751:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Reſurrection of their Bodies,</hi> (nor can the ſcope of the place, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, favour the interpreting of it concerning their ſtate on Earth) and ſince it cannot be underſtood of their Souls in their Bodies on Earth nor at the Reſurrection, then it muſt be meant of their Souls in their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated ſtate. And if in that ſtate they are, they are more perfect than before they were, they muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be more happy alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:179751:28"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The ſame Doctrine proved from</hi> Rev. 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HAving urged ſeveral Scriptures for my purpoſe, I ſhall now only add this unto them. And if any Perſon doubts whether this will prove the happy ſtate of Juſt Mens Souls in ſeparation from their Bodies, he muſt be a Man of doubtfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>But (for the buſineſs) let us note in what manner the truth was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted: <hi>I heard,</hi> ſaid St. <hi>John, a voice from Heaven ſaying to me, write, Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord from henceforth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:179751:28"/>
               <p>Note alſo that it is not ſpoken of Men as living on Earth or in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but of them as dying in the Lord, (in his Faith and Fear) <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is added, from henceforth (from the time of their dying.) And how can we think it would be ſaid, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe Dead, if they did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome bleſſed privilege by dying?</hi> if death did not bring more good to their Souls than hurt to their Bodies; then we have the Spirit aſſerting it, <hi>yea, ſaith the Spirit;</hi> Together with one part, or property, of their bleſſedneſs; <hi>they reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> (from all their troubles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.) And this Reſt muſt include a poſitive happineſs in the Love and Peace of their gracious God: For a meer Negative, or Privative Reſt, conſiſting in a bare Freedom from Pain and Trouble, is no more than the Beaſts partake of; when the Horſe is dead there's an end of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179751:29"/>wearineſs as well as his work. And I hope we may ſafely believe that a dead Chriſtian (that ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſuch in his life) is in a better ſtate preſently after Death than a dead Beaſt can be; and he whoſe Religion is any thing ſtronger than his Atheiſm will account this Text an evidence of it.</p>
               <p>And this ſhall ſuffice for Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the point, and I doubt not but it may be ſome ſatisfaction to thoſe that ſeek the truth in Love, and humbly implore the guidance of God's Holy Spirit. In the next place I am to make good my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and ſo to vindicate this truth from exceptions, and defend it from that violence which ſome have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:179751:29"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>The Happineſs of Juſt Mens Souls, in the ſtate of ſeparation, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS to contend for the truth is no unlawfull ſtrife (by clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and confirming it) ſo to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it againſt objections is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary. And I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome may not expect it.</p>
               <p>But before I anſwer Mens Cavils againſt this comfortable Doctrine, it may not be amiſs to ſay ſomething to thoſe that would diſſuade us from medling with matters of this nature. For to what purpoſe (ſay they) ſhould we trouble our ſelves about it? For if we believe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God ſhall have an Eternity of Happineſs after the Reſurrection,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179751:30"/>is not that ſufficient for us, whether our Souls can be happy in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration or not?</p>
               <p>Whether it is kindneſs or croſneſs, Religion or Sin, that moves men to talk after this rate, I ſhall not now enquire: Sure I am, It is our Duty to ſearch the Scriptures (and bleſſed be God for the liberty of doing ſo.) And certainly 'tis not below us to ſearch them for this purpoſe, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we may find ſatisfaction about it: which that we may, I truſt, will be acknowledged by the unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Reader. Things revealed do belong to us; and that this is revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led may eaſily be perceived by what has been inſiſted on about it. And he that grants it a truth will never deny it to be a comfortable one (whatſoever alſo Chriſtians may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue, methinks they ſhould not deſpiſe the Conſolations of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which will hold when other comforts fail). And though it be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179751:30"/>not very delightfull to deal with the confident cavils of deceived Sinners, yet to prevent their miſchief, I am willing to beſtow a few lines upon them. As for Scripture that they uſe to oppoſe this truth by, 'tis eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 6.5. <hi>In death there is no Remembrance of thee, and in the Grave who ſhall give thee Thanks?</hi> But muſt not they be very quick-ſighted that can find in the place of Darkneſs, an Argument againſt this encouraging Doctrine?</p>
               <p>But how little this Text maketh againſt it a few words will ſhew. For. 1. The Pſalmiſt doth not ſay, <hi>there is no Remembrance of God after Death,</hi> but thus <hi>[In Death there is no Remembrance of thee,</hi> viz. In that which is in Death or under Death's power, even the Body. Or, <hi>then there is no ſuch Remembrance of God as in the time of Life,</hi> for the Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, (or the like) and we know Negatives in Scripture are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179751:31"/>ſometimes meant only in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, or kind; as when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſays, <hi>there is no Peace to the Wicked:</hi> that is, <hi>no ſound well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Peace;</hi> for they may have Peace ſuch as it is, yea till ſudden deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come upon them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p>It follows, <hi>[Who ſhall give thee Thanks in the Grave]</hi> very ſure, that's no place for Praiſe: Yet nothing hinders but that the Soul after its departure, may have a bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the goodneſs of its God, and give him perpetual thanks, in its way and according to its capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Nor do thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt import any thing to the contrary:</p>
               <p>For as it was no part of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt's deſign to enquire into the ſtate of a ſeparated Soul (in that Text) ſo the Soul it ſelf, when ſeparated from the Body, is not in the Grave. Nor doth it anſwer to the word <hi>[Who]</hi> for the Soul is not a Perſon, but only a Conſtitutive part of the Perſon.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:179751:31"/>
               <p>With no leſs vanity is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.4. objected againſt this point <hi>[His Breath goes forth, he returneth to his Earth, and in that very day his thoughts Periſh]</hi> for Man's <hi>[thoughts]</hi> in that Scripture, need be extended no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his Earthly Thoughts, his Counſels, Projects and Policies, as to this world,
<note place="margin">Moller in loc.</note> which is enough to diſſuade us from put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our truſt in Man.</p>
               <p>Which alſo to doe was the purpoſe of the Pſalmiſt in that place. The Soul of the beſt Man would be pitifull Poor indeed, if after Death it ſhould be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all its thoughts (or think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power) and I am very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the Apoſtle would not have deſired to depart this Life, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death his Soul ſhould not have ſo much of Life as a thinking faculty containeth. In the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo there are ſome Texts ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179751:32"/>by theſe Men, but chiefly that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> 2 Tim. 4.8. <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me in that Day,</hi> (meaning the day of Judgment.)</p>
               <p>Therefore that Bleſſedneſs ſignified thereby (ſay they) is reſerved till that day, and not given before. But this Argument is ſo far wide that no art can make it come any thing cloſe for their purpoſe. For though we grant that the Faithfull have not their Happineſs till then (which is the moſt that it can prove.) Yet that doth not contradict the Happineſs of their Souls, in their ſeparated ſtate. And how happy ſoever their Souls be in that caſe, yet their Perſons cannot enjoy the State of Glory, till they are in the State of Perſonality, in the Union of their Bodies and Souls; which will not be till the Reſurrection.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179751:32"/>
               <p>There be, I confeſs, other Texts that ſome can fanſie this Doctrine to be oppoſed by; but I paſs them, becauſe they are ſo far from confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, that in my Opinion, they do not ſo much as ſeem to concern it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The point improved for Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Errours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt the many good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes for which the truth in hand may be ſerviceable, it may fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be conſidered for the diſproving ſome principles, that ſome People have too gladly entertained. 1. That of the Libertines [that the Soul at Death looſeth its very being, and vaniſheth into Air (or what they pleaſe) or, that it then hath a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179751:33"/>drowſie ſtate, if any, and ſleeps, as it were, in the Grave or other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces] Doctrines exactly calculated for the Meridian of Profaneneſs, and may indifferently ſerve for all bad practices. They are indeed of ſuch a diſmal Aſpect, and Malign Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that I can hardly compare them to any more fitly than thoſe that came out of the mouth of the <hi>Leviathan</hi> (for they look as ugly though not juſt like them.) And as one day their folly ſhall be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to all Men, ſo the preſent truth doth fully diſcover it.</p>
               <p>For if the Soul in its ſeparated ſtate be capable of Joy and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (as was proved) certainly then it looſeth not its Being, nor its Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. And well may he be deemed a ſenſeleſs Man here, that thinketh his Soul ſhall be ſo inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereafter.</p>
               <p>And as plainly doth it oppoſe the Doctrine of Purgatory, which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:179751:33"/>though <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his Brethren ſay hath its difficulties as to thoſe queſtions about it, which the Church has not determined, yet is ſtrongly aſſerted by them as a place of real puniſhment for the Souls of ſuch as ſhall ſee Happineſs at laſt; but muſt, in order to it, be Purged and Purified in that place of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Which can hardly need any other confutation than the proof of the happy ſtate of the Spirits of the juſt in their departure from their Bodies; which I hope hath been given from the Texts urged for that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:179751:34"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>For Trial of our ſelves, whether we are of the number of thoſe juſt ones, that may juſtly expect this approaching Felicity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce there is ſuch a happy ſtate for the juſt after Death, yea preſently after it; ſo as that Death it ſelf becomes their advantage, and leadeth their Souls into the bleſſed preſence of their Saviour: Since it is thus (I ſay) methinks it ſhould mightily move conſidering People to ſearch and try their ways, and ſtates, and ſee whether they are in ſuch a ſtate as may warrant them to lay claim to this <hi>Happineſs at Hand,</hi> which the word of our God diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to us. If it be reported (any thing credibly) that they who are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179751:34"/>ſo and ſo qualified ſhall have Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Preferments, how eaſily would they be brought to conſider whether they have the ſuppoſed Qualifications: at leaſt if they think themſelves capable of them (though at the ſame time they are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that Death will ſhortly diſgrace all worldly glory.) Much more ſhould Men try whether they can yet lay claim to that real Happineſs, that ſhall come quickly and laſt for ever.</p>
               <p>Now (as to this) They need no more to prove their Intereſt in it upon the account of Chriſt, than to prove themſelves to be truly Juſt, or Righteous Perſons. For 'tis the Juſt that ſhall come out of Trouble, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.13. 'Tis the upright one whoſe end is Peace, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.37. 'Tis the Righteous that hath hope in his Death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32 'Tis the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the Prophet tells us, ſhall enter into Peace, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.2. And we know by a Juſt or Righteous Man, the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179751:35"/>Scripture meaneth a Godly or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Man. There are but two ſorts, the <hi>Good,</hi> and the <hi>Bad,</hi> (in Scripture) which are commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Righteous and the Wicked, (<hi>Malachi</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.) The Juſt, and the Unjuſt (<hi>Math.</hi> 5.) So that the queſtion will be [who are theſe Juſt, Righteous, Religious People?] To which I ſhall Anſwer, 1. Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, 2. Poſitively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Negatively, They are not the Juſt ones that laugh at Religion, and mock at all that is called Holy; that are more taken with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> than with the precepts of the Bible; that are Enemies to the word of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and had rather hear of any thing almoſt than the holy truths thereof that moſt concern them; that ſay in their Hearts, their Tongues are their own; and are not affraid (of that fearfull Sin) to deſpiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:179751:35"/>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Jude</hi> 8. That drink as if they were made only to ſwallow, and keep Company (in their uſual courſe) till they are unfit for any Company; that love to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the ruines of others, and ſpare not the Poor, the Widow, and the Fatherleſs, to gratifie their greedy humours, and pleaſe their proud malicious Minds; that ſpight at the very Appearances of Piety, and rail at the moſt upright and inoffenſive Livers when they have put ſome hated Names upon them (as the Heathens of old baited Chriſtians with Dogs when they covered them all over with the Skins of wild Beaſts) that go about doing miſchief in abundance, inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a company of ugly, ſilly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull tales to ſet us at a diſtance from each other, and deſtroy the ſacred Bonds of Peace and Love; that have ſo deſperately debauched themſelves, and overcome their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179751:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:179751:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:179751:37"/>as to follow (without fear or ſhame) ſuch courſes as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens would cry out againſt; that provoke the moſt high in the moſt horrible manner, and imprecate on themſelves (on the ſmalleſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) the wrath of that great God which the proudeſt Devils tremble at. That theſe and ſuch like, are not the Juſt and Righteous ones, that the Scripture promiſeth Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to, is very evident in it ſelf. And I need no more to prove it, than to prove a Dunghill is not a Star. If therefore ſuch People ſhould have never ſo good thoughts of their States, yet in the day of God's Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, they ſhall ſee their Vanity, and underſtand with ſhame enough, that the holy one remembreth all their Wickedneſs, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall endeavour to ſhew what a Man may have, and yet not be a truly Juſt and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon, and afterwards add the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179751:37"/>Character of ſuch a one in various propoſitions.</p>
               <p>For the former: A Perſon may have outward peace and proſperity, and yet not be a Juſt Perſon; he may have very much of all earthly good, and not be good himſelf. Though proſperity is promiſed to the Godly ſo far as the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſees fitteſt, yet it commonly cometh to many of the Wicked, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.12. Behold theſe are the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, theſe proſper in the World. Yea the Tabernacles of Robbers did proſper, <hi>Job.</hi> 12.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A Man may have (as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperity, ſo) inward peace and yet not be a Righteous Man. That guilt may not much afflict the conſcience here, which hereafter may ſink the Soul into the horrid depths of endleſs ſorrows. The <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorian tells us that two of the verieſt Villains that ever that great Nation held, were obſerved
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179751:38"/>to die very quietly, though they ſhewed no ſigns of true Repentance; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of the wicked that when they ſay, Peace and Safety, then ſudden Deſtruction cometh upon them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. One may have a fair outſide and a good profeſſion, be a moral honeſt Man (as they call it) and ſo far from ſcandalous in the Worlds Eye, as to eſcape their ſeverer cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and yet not be a juſt Man (indeed and in a Scripture ſenſe.) It would be (in compariſon at leaſt) a very Happy Age, if all that ſeem good were ſo indeed: if all that are not ſcandalous in the ſight of the World, were Righteous in the ſight of God. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> whom we muſt ſurpaſs in goodneſs, if ever we would ſee the Kingdom of Heaven, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20.) Theſe I ſay, had (many of them) a fair outſide, and could not have gained ſuch a Reputation for Piety as we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:179751:38"/>know they had, if they had come ſhort of moral Men, and ſober Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and indeed they were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more than ſuch; for 'tis not eaſie to conceive a more curious frame of Religion, as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part of it than they had; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs their Praying and Faſting, their Alms and Obſervation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. and elſewhere. Yet they were not ſpoken of as the Righteous Servants of God: yea that very Text, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20.) ſhews plainly that they came ſhort of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, notwithſtanding all their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and performances.</p>
               <p>And if a Man may be morally honeſt, and outwardly Religious, and yet not be Righteous and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious indeed, O then (Chriſtian Reader) what ſhall we think of thoſe that are Scorners of Religion, and have ſcarce any ſhews of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them: that value the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture no more than a Play Book,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179751:39"/>and an Orthodox Sermon than an idle Story: that act contrary to the great Rules of Morality and Sober Reaſon, diſhonouring their God and themſelves, at once, by horrid Oaths and Imprecations, by Helliſh Railings, Lyes and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in their ordinary courſe; that call themſelves People of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and live as if they were made to diſgrace it, ſaying (once in a month or two) <hi>[I Believe in God]</hi> yet behaving themſelves daily as if they <hi>Believed</hi> there is no God; boaſting very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the Loyalty of their principles, yet ſeldom coming to Church to pray for their King; in a word, grinding the Faces of the poor and needy in the groſseſt manner) treating them with terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble threatnings, and diſcourſing them with Luciferian Loftineſs, when they humbly beg the money that they have honeſtly earned of them,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:179751:39"/>and beſeech it for their neceſſities ſake? O how far are theſe from the Juſt Man's path? And though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they may have a falſe peace, yet when Conſcience is awakened they may be forced to conſider (with confuſion enough) that their God is not to be mocked, and that he knoweth how to reſerve the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to the day of Judgment to be puniſhed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Man may have ſome kind of good motions, and good deſires, and yet not be a truly Juſt and Righteous Perſon. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf deſired <hi>Moſes</hi> to pray for him, and 'tis ſaid of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> that he <hi>Believed, Acts.</hi> 8.13. which muſt needs imply ſome good thoughts of the Chriſtian Faith, and ſome motion of his mind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it. And thoſe to whom the Holy Prophet was as a pleaſant Song (which argues that they had ſome delight in his Miniſtery, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179751:40"/>ſome deſire after it) yet are not ſpoken of as God's Righteous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: for 'tis added, <hi>They hear thy words but do them not, Ezech.</hi> 33.32. Divines, (I acknowledge) uſe to put a good Interpretation upon good deſires, and ſpeak often of their Acceptance in the ſight of God, when they write for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of afflicted Conſciences: But then thoſe good deſires are ſuppoſed to be ſound and well grounded, and attended with ſuitable endeavours, and an upright inoffenſive Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in the main: But as for thoſe good deſires that too many are apt to content themſelves with; as when they content themſelves to live ill, (in Sottiſh, Profane, Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and Injurious practices) and yet ſatisfie themſelves with this that they wiſh in ſome ſort that they could do better (and ſo hope that God accepteth the Will for the Deed in ſuch a caſe) This, I ſay, is a ſad
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179751:40"/>miſtake, and one of the moſt wretched deluſions that ever <hi>Satan</hi> deceived any Sinner with; for God doth abſolutely require Men, and chiefly Chriſtian Profeſſors to live well; and will never diſpence with it for the ſake of any good deſires; nor are our deſires truly good any further than they make us, truly and in the main, followers of that which is good. Nor can any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be accepted with God, which a Man may have while his heart is in love with any way of Wickedneſs. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me,</hi> Pſal. 66.18. Theſe things are ſo plain that there may ſeem little need to ſay any thing to clear or confirm them: yet becauſe 'tis the ſaddeſt thing imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for Men to be deceived to deſtruction by falſe Apprehenſions of their own goodneſs here on Earth, I ſhall add a few words more about it. Conſider therefore that as the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179751:41"/>Scripture in ſome places deſcribes the juſt by their good deſires (for 'tis little of good, for any to doe what is good againſt their Wills) ſo in other places, and more uſually it deſcribes them by good Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and upright doings. When the queſtion is put, <hi>Who ſhall dwell in God's Holy Hill,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.2.) 'tis anſwered, <hi>He that walketh uprightly and worketh Righteouſneſs.</hi> (Not he that faintly wiſheth to walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and in the mean time liveth wickedly, but he that ſo deſires it as to doe it in ſome meaſure, and in his ordinary courſe. So the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the parable that is ſtiled <hi>good</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> is intimated to have done well, and not only to have ſpoken well, or to have wiſhed his Maſters work well done, without any more concern about it. Thus alſo <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, Luk.</hi> 1.6. are commended for Righteous Perſons, not for having ſome good
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179751:41"/>thoughts of God's ways, or ſome uneffectual good wiſhes about them, but for walking in them, (verſ. 6) <hi>They were Righteous before God, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Commandments of the Lord. The Righteous</hi> (that are noted to be mercifull alſo) <hi>are ſpoken of as walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their uprightneſs, Eſay.</hi> 57.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Briefly, 'tis well doing, and not well wiſhing without it (where Ability and Opportunity is affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) that ſhall end well at laſt, and come off with Credit at the great day of Revelation: <hi>They that have done good ſhall come forth to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Life,</hi> Joh. 5.29.</p>
               <p>And the great reaſon why Men ſhall be judged according to their ways, may be ſuppoſed to be this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are the trueſt diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their deſires and diſpoſitions; (as the ſtream diſcovereth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Fountain whence it floweth) and the matter is clear in any other caſe: If, for inſtance,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:179751:42"/>one that hath took up Arms againſt his King, ſhould conſider what it is that he doth, how evil, how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, how ſcandalous it is, and ſo ſhould reſolve (and accordingly deſire) to ceaſe his Rebellion, and become a true Subject: yet if he does not ſo indeed, and actually lay down his Arms (it being a thing that lyeth in his power) he is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly no better than a Rebel ſtill, and muſt not think that his King will accept thoſe good deſires and Reſolutions that made him never a whit the better Man.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Man may doe ſome good deeds and yet not be in the number of the juſt. Poſſibly his goodneſs may be as the Morning Dew, when his Wickedneſs is more conſtant and prevailing. His common courſe may be Earthly and Senſual, yea Deviliſh too, though he ſometimes make a ſhift to ſtep out of <hi>Satan's</hi> path into ſome good action for his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179751:42"/>credit ſake, or the like ends. As we have the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> for examples of it, though they were the greateſt enemies our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had.</p>
               <p>It was ſaid of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> he did what was right in the ſight of the Lord, but not with a perfect (or upright) heart, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.2. Thus ſome will doe works of Juſtice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, and yet live in a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and common neglect of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Prayer, and publick Worſhip and Service toward God, and what is ſuch Mens Righteouſneſs worth, while 'tis ſo void of Religion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the God of Righteouſneſs? Some again will doe works of mercy towards the Poor, yet allow themſelves to rail at the Rich, and ſpight at any that are above them in the World; and what is ſuch Mens mercy worth?</p>
               <p>Are theſe juſt Men indeed that are ſo injurious to their God, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:179751:43"/>diſhonour him more in ſome ways than they honour him in others? We think that Man more an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my than a Friend that knowingly and uſually does us more hurt, than good. And our Religion, we know, engages us to mind (in its place) every part of God's revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Will, to keep a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God as well as Men, and towards one as well as another, <hi>Acts.</hi> 24.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. In ſhort, to live Godly, Righteouſly and Soberly in this preſent World, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>Having ſeen what good a Man may have and yet not be a good or juſt Man, I think it will be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable digreſſion to conſider what evil one may have and yet be ſuch indeed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Perſon may have variety of troubles, yea ſuch as the moſt and the worſt do ſeldom meet with, and yet be a juſt Perſon (Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179751:43"/>and accepted in the ſight of God) the ſtraits of time may be Tempeſtuous to thoſe to whom the Ocean of Eternity ſhall be calm enough. <hi>Many are the troubles of the Righteous,</hi> Pſ. 37. and we know the troubles of <hi>Job,</hi> that upright Man, were ſuch as few or none ever ſuffered the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Inward and Spiritual Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not at all inconſiſtent with the State of the juſt in this World. One may be full of doubts of his Salvation and fears of Hell, yea he may be under the extremity of theſe evils (and be ſwallowed up as it were in theſe depths of ſorrow) and yet be an Heir of Heavens joy. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſhews us, <hi>He had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered God's Terrours from his Youth,</hi> Pſal. 88.15. <hi>Job</hi> complained that <hi>the Terrours of God had ſet themſelves in array againſt him,</hi> 6.4. <hi>Terrours are turned upon me, they purſue my Soul,</hi> Chap. 30.15. adding (<hi>v.</hi> 17.)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179751:44"/>
                  <hi>My Bones are pierced in the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and my Sinews take no Reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A Chriſtian may be followed with great Temptations, yea with horrid and unheard-of ones, and yet may be a juſt Man. For it was ſo with our Lord himſelf. He was tempted to fall down and worſhip the unclean Spirit, and to caſt himſelf down from the Pinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Temple, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6.9. And if theſe things befell the Son of God, the vileſt Temptations may be managed againſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God. They that have grace in their hearts and favour in Heaven, may have their Heads fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with horrible thoughts (of God, Chriſt, Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And theſe thoughts being hated increaſe not their guilt, but their grief only, and <hi>Satan</hi> the ſuggeſter of them ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for them, and not the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humbled Sinners.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:179751:44"/>
               <p n="4">4. A Man may have much to doe with Sin, and find a great deal of evil in his Soul, (in affections, thoughts and paſſions) and yet be found in the number of the juſt. Not only diſturbing thoughts in Prayer and other Duties, but alſo many other evil affections and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations may be really in him, and yet he may be a Servant of God. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit</hi> (Corruption a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Grace) which ſuppoſeth ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſitions. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.21. ſays he of himſelf, <hi>When I would doe good, evil is preſent with me:</hi> Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the evil of his own heart, for the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth properly not the evil one <hi>Satan,</hi> but the evil thing Sin. To which may be added <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. where ſpeaking of that eminently Righteous Man <hi>Elias,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>He was a Man of like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with us</hi> — which ſeems to mean that he was ſubject to the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179751:45"/>ſame ſinfull paſſions that others are, and had them really though not Reigning in his Soul: ſuch as raſh anger, immoderate cares, inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate fears, impatient motions, and the like — That this is the meaning of it may be gueſſed by the 17. verſe, <hi>Elias was a Man ſubject to like paſſions as we are, and he prayed that it might not Rain for three years, and it Rained not:</hi> that is, God ſhewed ſuch a regard to his Prayers, though he were ſuch a one; now if we interpret it of the <hi>like</hi> paſſions only in a <hi>natural</hi> ſenſe (ſo as to have in him joy and fear and the reſt that belong to the nature of Man as ſuch, without any thing of Sin) this would be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wonder that his Prayers ſhould be thus heard; there being nothing more agreeable to the divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than to ſhew a great regard to the petitions of thoſe Creatures that are fully conformed to their Maker's
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179751:45"/>Will, and have nothing amiſs, or offenſive in them. But that God ſhould ſo regard the petitions of one that was ſubject to the like ſinfull paſſions as we are, this was <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous</hi> indeed, and a piece of unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able condeſcenſion in the moſt high and holy one: this therefore is moſt like to be the meaning of it.</p>
               <p>And if it were not ſo, it would be little encouragement to ſinfull Creatures, which I verily believe it was eſpecially written for. So that ſinfull affections and motions, where they are reſiſted and oppoſed, and accompanied with a conſcientious courſe in the main, are no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all that a Man is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the number of the <hi>Juſt.</hi> Whatſoever evils there may be, which do only hinder us in the ways of God, but do not ordinarily turn us out of them (or ſet our hearts againſt them) all theſe are not able to diſprove our ſincerity or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179751:46"/>deprive us of Acceptance with our gracious God. The Traveller that reſolveth, with God's Aſſiſtance, to go to ſuch and ſuch Towns (ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out and proceeding as he ought to doe) though he ſhould be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thruſt out of his way, or be forced to carry a Burden that makes him walk ſlowly and wearily in it, yet is in truth a Traveller towards thoſe places as much as if he went with the greateſt eaſe and ſpeed; ſo the Chriſtian that makes God his end, and the way of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments his common path to walk in, though he be clogg'd with Sin and compaſſed with Infirmity (and many ways hindered in running the Race that is ſet before him) yet is a Traveller towards Heaven truly ſo called, and ſhall one day ſee that City of God.</p>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:179751:46"/>
                  <head>An Appendix to the 8<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Section, being a Character of that Juſt Perſon whoſe Soul ſhall ſhortly be ſo Happy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. HE is an Enemy to unjuſt doings: He loves not the Work nor the Wages of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but has the great Law of [doing as he would be done by] written in his heart, and copied out in his Converſation. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, a Man can no more be called Juſt, than he can be called Wiſe without Wiſedom, or ſtrong without ſtrength. This therefore is fitter to be premiſed than proved, doubtleſs the upright Man will walk in uprightneſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Juſt Perſon is one of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Life: the Wiſedom of the Juſt will make a Man ſo, and not ſuffer him to live like a Sot while he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179751:47"/>for the Inheritance of the Saints. The Juſt Man will be Juſt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and will not ordinarily doe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to a Barrel to eſcape the Drunkards Songs or Cenſures He knows his God requires him to watch and be ſober (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.) and that it becomes him to be ſo as he is a Man, much more as a Chriſtian. The grace of God, where once it is a Teacher indeed, teaches the great Leſſon of living ſoberly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Juſt Man is a Godly Man too, and makes Conſcience of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God as well as Man his due. When the Scripture acquaints us that <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were Righteous People, it ſaith, <hi>they walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all the Commandments of the Lord, Luke</hi> 1.6. 'Twas not the Cuſtom of the World, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God that they choſe to walk by. The Juſt Man is (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Controverſie) a Man of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179751:47"/>and Conſcience reſpecteth God as well as Men, yea God in the firſt place, and Men for his ſake, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16. <hi>Herein I do exerciſe my ſelf to have a Conſcience void of offence towards God and towards Men,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. <hi>I have walked in all good Conſcience before God.</hi> The doors of the Temple, or Tabernacle, were the Gates of the Lord, and into them 'twas ſaid the Righteous ſhall enter (However the Wicked deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe them,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.20, 21. And when the Pſalmiſt had ſaid, <hi>Know ye that the Lord is God, it is he that hath made us,</hi> &amp;c. He preſently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth — <hi>Enter into his Gates with Thankſgiving, and into his Courts with Praiſe,</hi> Pſal. 100.3, 4. As if he had ſaid, ye do not acknowledge the Lord to be your God, and your ſelves his Creatures to any purpoſe, if ye deny him the Honour of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip and Praiſe. And in the New Teſtament what can be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:179751:48"/>more obſervable than the zeal that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf, that juſt one in the higheſt ſenſe, did ſhew for the honour of the Temple, the place of publick Service to God, driving the Traders out of it, pouring out the Changers Monies, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the Tables therein, <hi>John</hi> 2.15. It was ſtrange if ſome ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Hypocrites did not cenſure him very ſharply for it, and report him deſtitute of that meekneſs that the Servants of God ſhould ſhew forth; and perhaps it was ſo: for as he did more than is written in the Goſpel, ſo we have no reaſon to doubt but he ſuffered more than is written al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
                  <p>Surely then the Juſt Man will be juſt to his God, and gladly give him, in his conſtant courſe, the Glory due unto his Name. If therefore the Houſe of God be unto People as a place of contempt, his Day an idle time with them, and matters of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179751:48"/>vanity be ordinarily more pleaſing to them in it than the exerciſes of piety: then, (Reader) in ſpight of all their faireſt pretences, and ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt Speeches, I ſhall not fear to affirm that their Righteouſneſs and Religiouſneſs are much alike, and that both of them together are no more worth than the honeſty of a common Thief, when he hath no opportunity of ſtealing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He is one that makes Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of being ſubject to his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and is taught in the fear of God to Honour his King. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth not to ſeparate what God hath joyned together, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. They are ſpoken of as ſome of the worſer ſort of unjuſt People, that deſpiſe Dominion and ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, <hi>Jude</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Juſt Man is a mercifull Man alſo. They the Prophet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Righteous are noted to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull too. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.1. <hi>The Righteous
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:179751:49"/>periſh, and mercifull Men are taken away.</hi> The Juſt Man (whom Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtileth ſo) is certainly a good Man: and 'tis the nature of a good Man to have real compaſſions in his Soul. Yea, he is mercifull to his Beaſt alſo: <hi>A Righteous Man regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Life of his Beaſt,</hi> Prov. 12.10.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Juſt Man is an humble Man: though he often looketh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, yet he is lowly in heart whatſoever his Apparel be, he is cloathed with Humility. God will ſave the Humble Perſon, <hi>Job</hi> 22.29 and 'tis the Righteous to whom his Salvation belongeth. <hi>The Salvation of the Righteous is of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 37.39. <hi>Every one that is proud in Heart, is an Abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 16.5. But certainly the Juſt Man is not ſo.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. A Juſt Man is a Heavenly-minded Perſon, and would not be a Worldling for all the Earth, and the Sea is worth. Though he
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179751:49"/>thankfully accepteth Earthly Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, yet Spiritual and Heavenly are moſt in his eſteem. <hi>They that are after the Spirit do mind</hi> (chiefly) <hi>the things of the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.5. Accordingly the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the reſt of the faithfull as well as himſelf, ſaith 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. <hi>We look not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen, for the things that are ſeen are Temporal, but the things that are not ſeen are Eternal.</hi> Thoſe that elſewhere he ſo ſadly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented as to weep at the mention of them, (and whoſe ends were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,) were People that did mind earthly things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. that is, they minded theſe things moſt, and ſet their very hearts, as we call it, upon them. He that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually and practically loveth the Riches, Honours, or Pleaſures of the World more than God, and the Happineſs that is to be found in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying him in a State of perfect Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179751:50"/>is not a Saint for calling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Chriſtian, but a fooliſh Man for accounting himſelf ſo. Nor is there any diſpoſition that I know of that is more apparently contrary to the power of Godlineſs, and the renewed nature of a gracious Soul. He that is more at the command of his Covetouſneſs than of his God and his Conſcience, is like to appear amongſt the Diſobedient at laſt. Grace it ſelf cannot fit a Man for Happineſs any other way than by gaining his heart to God.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Juſt Man is ſo effectually fallen out with Sin, that no Art can reconcile him to any ways of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Wickedneſs, ſo as to chuſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to walk therein, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. <hi>The Juſt Man's path is as the Shining Light.</hi> Therefore ſurely he doth not give himſelf over to follow the Works of Darkneſs, nor walk in the way of Damnation. And how can we conceive the contrary without
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179751:50"/>ſuppoſing God's Grace to be given him in vain? For how could he live worſe than ſo, if he were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of it? The Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth God's Righteous Servants by their true devotedneſs of him, and their unfeigned choice of his ways to walk in (which cannot ſtand with any common courſe of known Wickedneſs,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38. <hi>Stabliſh thy word to thy Servant who is devoted to thy Fear.</hi> It was the great evidence of the Grace of God in the <hi>Macedonians</hi> that they gave themſelves up unto the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. 5 The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> alſo ſetteth forth his Religion by the chief Bent of his Will to it, ſaying, <hi>I have choſen thy Precepts; I have choſen the way of Truth,</hi> Pſal. 119.13.30. The wicked are Perſons of the contrary Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They did not chuſe the fear of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. and, they choſe the thing in which he delighted not (<hi>i.e.</hi> the way that he hated) <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.12.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:179751:51"/>
                  <p n="9">9. The Juſt Man in all and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, hath an Eye to the Juſt one: he hath his Faith and Love fixed upon that infinitely amiable object <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous.</hi> If you could give him the uttermoſt of this World's good, and aſſure him to keep it (in eaſe and peace) ten thouſand years together, yet Chriſt is more to him than all this; yea, 'tis as nothing, and vanity in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of him. All our Religion, I dare ſay, is worth very little, if Chriſt be not more valuable with us than all this World: for elſe we are Worldlings in Heart, and mind earthly things in ſuch a ſad ſenſe, that Deſtruction is the end it tends to, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. The Wiſedom of the Juſt will make a Man truly and ſpiritually acquainted with his own unworthineſs, and ſinſulneſs, ſo as to know for certain that he is by Nature a Child of Wrath, and lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to eternal Damnation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179751:51"/>to ſee more need of Chriſt than his Eye hath of Light, or his Body of Breath. His Heart yields aſſent to that bleſſed word that ſhews him to be a Mediatour and Saviour for Sinners, and the Deliverer from the Wrath to come, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. Yea the Authour of Eternal Salvation, (which infinitely exceeds all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good,) <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly his People have eſteemed of him as the chiefeſt of ten thouſands, as altogether lovely, <hi>Cantic.</hi> 5.10.16. St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s great deſire was to be found in Chriſt, not having his own Righteouſneſs (to truſt to) <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. counting all things, as loſs, that he might Win Chriſt. St. <hi>Peter</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tells us that to them that believe, Chriſt is precious (that is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. For we do, in effect, wholly undervalue him if we prefer any thing of the Earth before him. Thus, Reader, I have given thee the Character of that Juſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:179751:52"/>(in Heart and Life) that ſhall be happy after Death; and if it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agrees to thee, thou art in ſome meaſure happy here, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and nothing ſhall make thee miſerable. Thou maiſt (if ſuch) ſafely lay claim to the comforts of a Chriſtian, and needeſt not to live like a Fool or a Slave, in fear (I mean) of Poverty and Want, of Scorn and Contempt, of any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity or Extremity whatſoever. For to them that walk uprightly: The Lord God himſelf, is a Sun and a Shield, and will never fail them nor forſake them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:179751:52"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Shewing the uſefulneſs of the point in two other particulars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the next place, it may occaſion us to conſider the different ends of the Righteous and the Wicked. They may (I grant) be alike <hi>in</hi> their ends, but they will not be alike <hi>afterwards.</hi> Though they may die the ſame kind of Death, yet Death will not be the ſame to both; the one ſhall be a gainer by it, and be with Chriſt; which is far better than any condition here: the other ſhall be a looſer by it, and be in greater miſery than any he feared in this World. That which by any means cuts the thread of his Life, caſts down alſo all the Pillars of his hope, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 11.7. <hi>When a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179751:53"/>Wicked Man dyeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Wicked Man's miſery after Death.</note> 
                  <hi>his Expectation ſhall Periſh, and the hope of unjuſt Men Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth.</hi> As then he is deprived of all his Wealth and Honour, Sport and Pleaſure, and all that outward good or comfort which here he took any content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in; ſo his departed Soul will find nothing to ſupply the want of them. 'Tis true: It hath to doe with God, but not in a way of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and favour; and therefore his preſence will not comfort it in the abſence of earthly comforts. <hi>The Spirit,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, returns to God that gave it;</hi> that's ſpoken of the Spirit, or Soul of Man, in general, whether good or bad. The Spirit of a good Man returneth to God as to a gracious Father, the Spirit of a bad Man as to a Righteous Judge and diſpoſer of it. And we cannot imagine that the Soul of one that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:179751:53"/>would never return (in a holy ſenſe) in his life time ſhould return to God, in a happy ſenſe, when his life is ended. For he will recompenſe him according to his ways, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>and hath revealed his Wrath againſt all the ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Men,</hi> Rom. 1.18. 'Tis ſaid of the unbeliever, ſo continuing, <hi>that the Wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.36. And every ungodly Man (we doubt not) is an unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in a Scripture ſenſe, though he cares not to think ſo ill of himſelf. And what wonder is it if the holy one ſhew his high diſpleaſure againſt the departed Soul of that Sinner, that would not Religiouſly depart from Evil, nor was ever reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through Jeſus Chriſt? Now what a dreadfull caſe will this be? What a terrible taking will a guilty Impenitent Soul be in, when it ſees it ſelf in the Regions of Eternal Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? When it hath loſt all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:179751:54"/>and comfortable Expectations, and ſhall never ſee any more good: when Money and Lands, when Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Friends, when Time and Hope, and all is gone! O what deep diſtreſs, what ſubſtantial ſorrows will it be filled with, when 'tis compaſt about with miſeries un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and utterly ſwallowed up (without help or hope) in the depths of God's revenging Wrath? —Conſider of it, Reader, in the fear of God, and never let thy Soul be ſatisfied without that mercy and grace which may fit thee to eſcape ſuch a fearfull condition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may alſo keep us from won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring at, (or at leaſt from ſtumbling at) the troubles of true obedient Chriſtians in this World. They come on them, many times, thick and threefold (as we call it) and are ſo far from moving the careleſs World to pity them, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them rather (but too common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179751:54"/>to the utmoſt ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p>Sometimes alſo they are ready to Blaſpheme (on that occaſion) and ſay, Behold, what good doth all their Godlineſs do them? For, how miſerably do they live? and who is there round about that have more ſorrows and grievances than many of thoſe that make ſo much adoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion? But aſſuredly all this will not warrant them to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe Religion, or thoſe that love and follow it. For beſides other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations that might be urged, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Their remaining ſinfulneſs which maketh the chaſtiſements of their Heavenly Father needfull for them (with that moſt wiſe providence and Fatherly love that ordereth and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them) together with the nature of Sin it ſelf that makes them worthy of more and greater ſufferings than in this mortal life they can ever bear; <hi>Death eternal being the wages of Sin,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:179751:55"/>Rom 6.23. I ſay, beſides theſe and the like conſiderations that may be urged, the ſhortneſs of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the certainty of their Souls Happineſs after Death, may abundantly ſatisfie them: and is more than ſufficient to countervail the ſaddeſt ſufferings of this mortal State, (as will farther be evinced by the nature and property of that Felicity, which in its place with God's Aſſiſtance I ſhall endeavour to explicate)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>Being a perſwaſive to ſeveral great Duties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE truth of the preſent point may be looked on as a true
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:179751:55"/>and juſt ground for Chriſtian prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices; and 'tis great pity but Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould be ſomewhat the better for a point of ſo much comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Goodneſs. Here therefore I may fitly endeavour to engage my ſelf and others to the duties following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Patience under God's afflicting hand (whether by outward or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles) Men of ordinary prudence can follow very unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant methods of Phyſick from the meer proſpect of that eaſe and health which they hope, in time, to find by ſo doing (though none do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them health, much leſs aſſure them of the continuance of it How ſhould a Chriſtian then endeavour (more and more) that patience may have its perfect work, when he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees by Faith that bleſſed Reſt which his Soul ſhall have after death hath ſeized upon his Body; and hath the word of God to aſſure him that this
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:179751:56"/>happineſs ſhall never end, but be compleated at the Reſurrection of the juſt, when their waſted Bodies ſhall forſake their dark Priſons, and <hi>Shine as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father,</hi> Mat. 13.43. He may therefore ſay with chearfulneſs as once a worthy Servant of Chriſt [Hold out Faith and Patience, for your work will ſhortly be at an end.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Duty of Charity ſhould hence be enforced upon us according to our place and power. What if Men be never ſo unworthy or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, yet Chriſtians ſhould be ready to extend their Charity to them, in any reaſonable way, for the ſake of that good God who will do them ſo much good after death. How can they do leſs than ſhew forth real compaſſions (on all fit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions) yea towards their very names, if they find them wronged therein, when they remember their heavenly Father's Love, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:179751:56"/>how ſhortly he will receive their immortal Souls, and Crown them with his tendereſt mercies?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Upright living in the general: how ſhould this engage a Chriſtian to honour his God what he can, and (as the Apoſtle exhorts) to do all to his Glory: to live by Faith and walk in Love, and be ready to every good work? For as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Serve the Lord in truth with all your heart, for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what great things he hath done for you;</hi> How fitly then may I ſay to ſuch a one, be diligent in thy duty, and lead thy life to the glory of that gracious God who will ſatisfie thy Soul with his glorious goodneſs when once it hath left this ſinfull World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It ſhould make a Chriſtian willing (yea glad) to glorifie his God by dying for his truth (if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſhould call him to it.) Life is ſweet, (ſays the Proverb) and to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:179751:57"/>part with it when we can keep it is commonly counted a hard Chapter: and 'tis really a principal part of ſelf denial. But 'tis no more than a Chriſtian ought to be content to practiſe (though Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan</hi> would render it needleſs) when God calls him to it, and when he cannot keep his Life without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the truth or doing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome other way; and as in ſuch caſes he ſhould think himſelf bound to it by Chriſt's dying for him (whoſe death was more grievous than the death of any Man elſe, and whoſe life was more precious than the life of all created Beings;) ſo he ſhould be encouraged to it by acting his faith upon the truth in hand: for why ſhould he either think it much or think it ſad, to part with his life for the honour of that immortal Majeſty whoſe preſence and favour is his whole Felicity, and ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be to his departed Soul an Ocean
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:179751:57"/>of Eternal Peace and Pleaſures?</p>
               <p n="5">5. It ſhould move a Chriſtian to be content under the ordinary croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this life, and particularly pains and ſickneſſes and ſpightfull cauſeleſs aſperſions and diſgraces.</p>
               <p>No Affliction (we confeſs) is in it ſelf joyous but grievous; (and therefore People are not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for being ſenſible of them; nor are thoſe kind of Perſons wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiſe, nor yet very charitable, that cenſure their Neighbours of groſs impatience for crying out in an extremity of pain) though, I ſay, no Afflictions, or thoſe inſtanced in, are in themſelves any other than matters of grievance, yet a Chriſtian has no cauſe to be diſcontent or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged: for his mind may receive great ſatisfaction when his Body can receive no eaſe; and why ſhould he faint at thoſe Tribulations that ſhall ſo ſhortly have an end, and a happy end too?</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:179751:58"/>
               <p>For however his Body be tired with Sickneſſes, and his Name abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the baſeſt Tongues, yet e're long his Soul ſhall have Reſt enough, yea and credit enough alſo amongſt the excellent Inhabitants of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen-World when once it hath put off its Earthly Tabernacle.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It ſhould move Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to take care of their Childrens ſpiritual welfare, and ſee that they be brought up in the Knowledge of God, and the Inſtructions of that ſacred word, <hi>Which is able to make them Wiſe to Salvation,</hi> 2 Tim 3.15. And ſo tends to prepare them for a happy immortality when this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal life is paſſed away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:179751:58"/>
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>Containing the Reſolution of two great Queſtions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I thought to have gone on in the ſmooth track of duties and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts ariſing from the Doctrine in hand: but on ſecond thoughts I was willing to reſolve (ſo far as the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my opinion of) ſome Queries relating to the preſent point.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether the Souls of the Juſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death, do go ſo immediately and directly to Heaven (or are ſo confined and limited) as to have nothing to do e at any time in this lower World?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the Reſt and Joy which they have after Death be perfect or not?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:179751:59"/>
               <p>Concerning theſe I deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be of my mind no farther than he can ſee ſome reaſon for it. As to the former, the moſt common opinion (I think) is, that ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Souls have no more to doe with any on Earth, or have no preſence with them (nor appearance to them) at any time, or on any account.</p>
               <p>But with me the ſaying of it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the proving of it ſignifies but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: and I know no Argument they being for it that my reaſon is ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in. I therefore conceive the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to be true: [that holy Souls after death may be at ſome times, and on ſome occaſions, preſent with Men in this World, appear to them and converſe with them] (though I believe it is not ordinary, nor ought to be expected by any.) And ſince there's no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> better way to prove a thing may be, than to prove that it hath been; I ſhall therefore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:179751:59"/>offer what to me ſeemeth conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for that purpoſe. And firſt: That Text of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> 17.3. <hi>There appeared</hi> (ſays the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt) <hi>unto them Moſes and Elias talking with them. — Moſes</hi> then appeared at Chriſt's Transfiguration: now we read that <hi>Moſes</hi> dyed, and was buried in the Land of <hi>Moab, Deut.</hi> 34.5. And if then he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his Body, he muſt have been raiſed from the Dead at that time: but Scripture tells us no ſuch thing, which in all probability it would have done if it had been ſo. There is therefore as great a probability that he then appeared in his Soul only. And I find the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> (in Contempl. on the Transfiguration) expreſs himſelf in this ſort; [<hi>Moſes</hi> did then appear, but whether in the Body, or out of the Body I cannot tell.] Thereby granting the latter might be as well as the former: and it is no abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:179751:60"/>for me to ſuppoſe that poſſible which ſo excellent an Author judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo.</p>
               <p>If any ſhould ask, how can a Soul being a ſpiritual ſubſtance, appear in the World? perhaps I may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (in like manner) I cannot tell: and if I, nor others cannot tell the manner of it, yet that diſproves not the reality of the thing. I know the Spider makes his Web, yet I do not tell Men (nor they me) how he makes it, nor yet of what matter. And if ſuch Cavillers would tell us how Angels do appear (that are as far from all eſſential corporeity, as the Souls of Men) we might the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſhew them how Souls may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. And thus much alſo I will add, that an eminent Divine aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me that the beſt Philoſophers he knew were of opinion, that the Souls of Men removed from their Natural Bodies, are embodied (as it were) in Aerial Vehicles; and that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:179751:60"/>was of the ſame Judgment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That of <hi>Samuel</hi> appearing to <hi>Saul,</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.12, 13, 14.) may fitly be urged. For the Scripture gives no cauſe to believe that <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>'s Body was then raiſed from the Dead, (nor do I find Expoſitors ſuppoſing ſuch a thing) it may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well be thought it was <hi>Samuel</hi> in <hi>Soul</hi> only. For the context ſeems to evince that it was <hi>Samuel really:</hi> The Apparition being called by no other name, as oft as 'tis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, — verſ. 12. <hi>When the Woman ſaw Samuel,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>And Saul per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it was Samuel;</hi> and thrice more in the other verſes 'tis ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. I know the contrary minded will have <hi>Samuel</hi> to be meant of ſomewhat elſe, either the Witches Familiar, or <hi>Satan</hi> in his ſhape, or ſome cunning piece that was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Saul</hi> with I know not what extraordinary Arts and Tricks, (as Mr. <hi>Scott</hi> and Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:179751:61"/>we ſhould think.) But if this be a warrantable way of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Scripture, I ſhall hardly know what is not; and let any intelligent Perſon judge whether by ſuch a way of interpreting, the plaineſt Hiſtory in Scripture (or elſewhere) may not be ſpoiled; And let it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that <hi>He</hi> that called it <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> ſo often was the holy Pen-man of that part of Scripture. And the Letter is to be inſiſted on, if there be nothing in that context, or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, to enforce the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; I am alſo the proner to think there is no ſuch thing, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the inſufficiency (if I much miſtake not) of the beſt Anſwers that are given by Writers of great Judgment and Acuteneſs in other matters: as Dr. <hi>Willet, Chamierus,</hi> and the <hi>Anti-Racovianist Nichol. Arnoldus</hi> in his Notes upon the place. Whoſe Anſwer being brief, (and yet the ſubſtance of what the others
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:179751:61"/>ſay) I ſhall (with due reſpect to his Name and Works) humbly take leave to examine. Well then:
<note place="margin">in Lib. cui tit. Lux in Tenebris.</note> It muſt not be thought that it was <hi>Samuel</hi> in <hi>his Soul,</hi> that there had to doe with <hi>Saul.</hi> This the learned Author will not grant, and gives the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reaſons as (1) <hi>Quia ſic ſubjectus fuiſſet Pythoniſſae:</hi> Becauſe (ſays he) if ſo, he ſhould have been Subject to the Witch of <hi>Endor;</hi> whereas ſuch a Servant of God was not, in his Soul ſubject to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> True indeed: He was not thus ſubject to her, nor doth that Scripture imply any ſuch thing. For it is not ſaid that <hi>Samuel</hi> came at her command; yea the contrary is intimated: for when he that is called <hi>Samuel</hi> appeared, <hi>the Woman</hi> ('tis ſaid) <hi>cryed out with a loud voice:</hi> a ſign ſhe was ſurpriſed, by ſeeing what ſhe was not wont to ſee (and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:179751:62"/>perhaps before ſhe had gone over all the methods of her Inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,) doubtleſs the appearance of her Familiar in humane ſhape (or any thing elſe that was uſual in her Magical Contrivances) was not like to have been ſuch an Afrightment to her.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Anſ. — <hi>Paſſus eſt ſe Adorari,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Samuel</hi> here, (ſays he) ſuffered <hi>Saul</hi> to worſhip him. But true <hi>Samuel,</hi> though <hi>in Soul</hi> only, would not have ſuffered ſuch a thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Indeed the holy Soul of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> Would not have conſented to ſuch a thing: but 'tis poſſible for it (for ought I know) to have ſuffered ſuch a thing. The beſt of God's Servants, in ſome caſes may let a Sin paſs without a formal reproof. (Not to eſpouſe the opinion of thoſe that ſay, Duty properly reſpects the Perſon, not a part of him. <hi>Lex datur perſonis.</hi>) 2. How knows any
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:179751:62"/>Man that this apparition did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>Saul</hi> for <hi>Worſhipping</hi> it if he did ſo indeed: For there is no neceſſity of ſuppoſing that not to have been done, which the Scripture doth not ſay <hi>was</hi> done. We read of our Saviour, that he did many things (meaning, no doubt, many great and wonderfull ones) that are not written, or recorded, <hi>John</hi> 21. And whereas ſome conceive that <hi>Saul</hi>'s act was only an act of reverence and reſpect, and not of worſhip or adoration, they are like enough to be in the right; and I am confident the expreſſion (in the 14 verſe) <hi>[He ſtoopt with his Face to the ground, and bowed himſelf]</hi> doth not enforce the contrary.</p>
               <p>His 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Anſ. <hi>Quia Sauli non Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondebat,</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe (ſays he) God refuſed to Anſwer <hi>Saul</hi> by any of the Prophets then living: much leſs then would he do it by the dead, and <hi>Luke.</hi> 16. Such a thing was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:179751:63"/>to the rich Man that requeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> That ſaying [The Lord anſwered him not] may, according to the ſcope of the place, be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted of anſwering <hi>Saul,</hi> as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, or in a comfortable way as t'was ſaid to a wicked People, <hi>When ye make many Prayers, I will not hear,</hi> Eſay. 1.15.</p>
               <p>And though <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. we are taught to attend to the Scripture, and not to expect information from Saints departed; yet this hinders not but that the Soul of a Saint in an <hi>extraordinary</hi> caſe, may have ſome converſe with the living in this World. And I have read in a good Author, that ſome of thoſe Angels that Scripture tells us appeared to People, were probably the Spirits of Juſt Men, called Angels only from their Office of Meſſage and Miniſtration. Thus Reader, I have given thee my thoughts in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:179751:63"/>and if thou ſheweſt me that I have erred herein, I ſhall willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owe thee, and pay thee, my thanks, And if I am (herein) out of the way, yet I am not alone: ſome of my betters are of the ſame mind, and particularly the famous Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher and Divine Dr. <hi>Henry More.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now only (as to this) add a remarkable Hiſtory (mentioned by a good Author) as followeth [One Mr. <hi>Watkinſon</hi> a Religious Man had a Daughter, whom he dearly loved, married to a Man at <hi>York</hi> (He then living in <hi>London</hi>) She came ſeveral times to viſit her Father: and the laſt viſit ſhe made, ſhe ſaid, at par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that ſhe feared ſhe ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee him more in this World. To which he anſwered, if he died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her, in caſe God would permit: the Dead to ſee the Living, he would ſurely ſee her once more.</p>
               <p>When he had been dead about half a year, in a night when ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>could
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:179751:64"/>not ſleep, the Chamber grew lighter and lighter; and being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly awake, ſhe ſaw her Father ſtand by her, who called her as he uſed to do, ſaying <hi>[Did I not tell you I would ſee you again?]</hi> She called him Father, and talked of many things. He bad her be Patient, and Dutifull to her Mother; He alſo bad her ſpeak what ſhe deſired at that time, becauſe he muſt ſhortly leave her; and then he ſhould meet her no more till they met in the Kingdom of God: and ſo at length the Chamber grew darker, and he was gone.]</p>
               <p>I know very well that Men of large Conſciences have a very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row belief of matters of this nature, (for the moſt part.) And I doubt not but the Atheiſtical Leviathaniſts of this Age are ready to laugh at ſuch a Relation; but I dare ſay, 'tis not the leſs credible for that. For as it was the ſubſtance of a Letter
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:179751:64"/>written to a Doctor of Divinity, ſo 'tis recorded by a very ingenious, and judicious Author Mr. <hi>Joſeph Glanvil,</hi> with theſe words at the end of it [I was told this with great aſſurance by Dr. <hi>Ruſt,</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Dromore,</hi> and was not credulous in theſe things.] Now though theſe Men had a deſign to promote the intereſt of Religion, yet 'tis verily thought they were not ſo unwiſe or unworthy as to endeavour it by frivolous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded reports. (Thus to the firſt Queſtion)</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Whether the Reſt and Joy of Juſt Mens Souls in their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated State, be perfect or not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is propoſed by ſeveral Writers, and particularly <hi>Buchan in Loc. Com.</hi> and <hi>Alſtedius</hi> in <hi>Theol. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemicâ:</hi> and is determined in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative. <hi>Inchoatâ Beatitudine,</hi> &amp;c. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:179751:65"/>uſe the word <hi>Incompleta.</hi> They enjoy (ſay theſe) the beginning of Bleſſedneſs, or an imperfect Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs — Thoſe that like this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (for me) may make the moſt of it, and reap all the comfort that it can afford: for my part I muſt needs ſay I do not admire it. And now I ſhall take leave to declare my Sentiments herein (with ſubmiſſion to better Judgments, and a Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be farther informed.) And (1.) by way of Conceſſion: I grant that the perfection of happineſs, properly ſo called, or in reſpect of the <hi>Compoſitum,</hi> or whole Man, is reſerved to the day of Judgment. <hi>Then the Lord will give his Righteous Servants the Crown of Righteouſneſs, and the eternal weight of Glory, as St.</hi> Paul ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>(2.) I grant there is a ſtate of Chriſtians in this Life that may be called a Bleſſedneſs, which yet is accompanied with no ſmall imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:179751:65"/>becauſe they daily lodge an Enemy of God, and have ſin dwelling in them. <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin we deceive our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (3.) that a holy Soul after death has not the perfection of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, or leſs of Happineſs than it needeth or deſireth, this I cannot comply with. Here therefore I ſhall attempt to prove that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Souls of the Juſt are in a State of perfect Happineſs, and have all that ſpiritual comfort from the God of all comfort, which on any account they have need of, (and ſuch a Happineſs I think we may juſtly call perfect, and is all that I wiſh to my own Soul in its abſence from the Body.)</p>
               <p>Now (for this) let us conſider the ſtate of Sanctified Souls after their removal from their Bodies. They have certainly Life, and Senſe, and Knowledge, and all the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial perfections that belong to them
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:179751:66"/>as ſpiritual ſubſtances. St. <hi>Stephen</hi> (doubtleſs) would not have ſaid (when his Enemies were killing him) <hi>Lord Jeſus, Receive my Spirit,</hi> if he had not believed that his Soul ſhould continue in its ſpiritual Being after his Body was dead. Now the Souls of ſuch, if they have not all the Happineſs that they <hi>need,</hi> then they muſt know ſo much or not; if we ſay they do <hi>not</hi> know it, we ſhall hardly prove that they know any thing elſe: and ſo comply with the Socinian Dream, of the Souls ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping after death.</p>
               <p>And (in reaſon) what are they more like to know than their own State? But if then they know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deſtitute of any Happineſs that they need, that knowledge muſt be matter of trouble and diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto them; and ſo (at that rate) the Souls of the Juſt ſhall be in part really unhappy, which thoſe that judge of them by the Scriptures will not believe.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:179751:66"/>
               <p n="2">2. If in their ſeparated State they have a perfect enjoyment of God, they muſt be perfectly happy: (by the confeſſion of all thoſe that know wherein Happineſs conſiſteth.) And that in that State they have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect enjoyment of God, is (one would think) no hard matter to make evident. For nothing but ſin can hinder the Soul from a perfect Communion with God, and comfort in Him. The Prophet tells the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of nothing but their <hi>Iniquities that could ſeparate between them and their God</hi> (he means apparently in point of comfort, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 59.2. But their iniquities (we have ſeen alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) do not follow them into the other World; their Souls are not under the defilements of ſin, when they leave the Body and go into the glorious preſence of the holy one. The Apoſtle calls them <hi>the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect,</hi> Heb. 12. and the Pſalmiſt tells us <hi>no evil ſhall dwell with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:179751:67"/>
               <p n="3">3. To be ever with the Lord, (in his ſpecial glorious preſence) is ſpoken of as the very top of our Felicity, and the principal matter of a Chriſtian's Comfort, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17, 18. And this Happineſs the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Spirits of the Juſt do partake of— <hi>To depart and be with Chriſt</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 1.23. and in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Deſiring rather to be abſent from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to be preſent with the Lord.</hi> If therefore the one proveth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Happineſs of the whole Man as ſuch, the other as well proveth the perfect Happineſs of the Soul as ſuch. Go on therefore, O Faithfull Chriſtian, in thy Chriſtian courſe, with Faithfulneſs and Diligence, with Chriſtian courage and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and let thy Soul magnifie the Lord, for it ſhall ſhortly want for no Felicity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:179751:67"/>
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>Treating of the Nature of this Happineſs, and the Joy that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing come unto theſe points I am in the depths indeed: and may well ſay, as St. <hi>Paul, who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving engaged in this Service, 'tis fit I ſhould go on with it, and perform it as God ſhall enable me.</p>
               <p>Here then, I am to conſider the happy privileges of a Sanctified Soul in its ſtate of Separation.</p>
               <p>And (1.) its Sanctification; I mean full and perfect by which it is freed from all the evil of ſin for the preſent, and all the danger of it for the future, as the Apoſtle calls them, <hi>the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:179751:68"/>(Heb. 12.23.) That this is meant of the Souls of the faithfull, is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally granted (and 'tis common in Scripture for the Soul to be ſpoken of under the name of Spirit: <hi>The duſt (the Body) ſhall return to the Earth, but the Spirit ſhall return to God that gave it,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.7.) And St. <hi>Stephen</hi> in like ſort commended his Soul to his Saviour, <hi>Lord Jeſus, receive my Spirit,</hi> Acts. 7.59. And, in that Text to the <hi>Hebrews [The Spirits of Juſt Men]</hi> can ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their Souls, becauſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of Angels in the verſe before, from whom therefore they are plainly diſtinguiſhed. And <hi>[their being made perfect]</hi> muſt needs be meant, of perfection in Grace and Holineſs: for as to any perfection in a natural ſenſe, they had it as much before in this World (yea the ſtate of the Soul in its Separation, without the perfection of Grace in it, may be thought to be a ſtate of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:179751:68"/>greater imperfection than before it was in.) Now ponder with thy ſelf, Reader, of this particular, and think what a bleſſed condition this muſt be</p>
               <p>If he is ſtiled <hi>Bleſſed, whoſe Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is forgiven,</hi> Pſal. 32.1. How Bleſſed then may they be accounted that have all their Iniquities par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and removed alſo? What a Happineſs is it, to be freed from all poſſibility of ſinning? If St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much lamented the In-being of Sin, complaining <hi>that when he would do good, evil was preſent with him,</hi> (Rom. 7.) and called himſelf <hi>Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Man for that very reaſon. How glad (may we think) would he have been, if at that very hour, he could have aſſured himſelf that he ſhould never be troubled with it any more? a privilege which after death his Soul was perfectly inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in. If the poor Man that I have read of, was ſo much delighted to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:179751:69"/>behold the Face of that Phyſician that had cured him of his fainting Sleeps, and frightfull Dreams; O then with what tranſcendent Joy and Gladneſs will a gracious Soul reflect upon the Love of its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, when he hath freed it from all degrees of ſinfulneſs, and healed all its Infirmities for ever! Oh what ſacred and ſatisfying Irradia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will it receive from the Sun of Righteouſneſs, when the Spirit of Glory hath perfected all its Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and delivered it from all the darkneſs of ſin! And in being free from ſin, it ſhall be free from all other evils (as he that is freed from his Debt is ſecured from all arreſts and troubles that relate to it) for whatſoever our God may be pleaſed to doe out of Sovereignty (and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to his Creature's ſin) as 'tis ſuppoſed <hi>Job</hi>'s Afflictions came on him in that way: Yet Divines agree that God did never lay Afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:179751:69"/>on his People but while they had ſin dwelling in them; ſo that the Souls of his Servants, after Death, are rid of all other evil, as well as of ſin. They ſhall then be no more diſturbed by any Enemies of their Peace; the Regions of the unſeen World they are then in, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Serene: The Ocean of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall be calm and comfortable to them; Then they ſhall have no more to doe with the Temptations of <hi>Satan,</hi> the Mocks of the Profane, the Snarls and Cenſures of proud-hearted Hypocrites. Theſe ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the upright no farther than the Grave: <hi>For their end is Peace,</hi> Pſal. 37.37. How found and ſubſtantial will the Soul's Joy be when it ſees it ſelf ſafe in the Arms of God's Love, beyond the ſphere of ſin and ſorrow? which ſhould move it to bear the more contentedly the Troubles and Temptations of this Tranſitory Life.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:179751:70"/>
               <p>In particular, the gracious Soul ſhall then have the excellencies that are moſt eſſential to true Happineſs, and be perfected in the Knowledge and love of God in Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, though he knew much more of Chriſt than moſt ever did, or ſhall do in this World, and had the Revelations of things too great to be uttered, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.) Yet his knowledge had a real imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection at the ſame time. <hi>We know but in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Now I know in part,</hi> but (as it follows) <hi>then I ſhall know as I am known.</hi> I will not play the Critick on that phraſe, nor ſearch curiouſly into the depths of it: 'tis, for our purpoſe, clear enough; for it muſt be meant of <hi>perfection</hi> of knowledge, becauſe 'tis oppoſed to a knowing in <hi>part.</hi> If any ſay it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood eſpecially of the ſtate at the Reſurrection, I ſhall not gainſay it. But I ſee not why it may not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:179751:70"/>alſo to the Soul in its Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For as the particle <hi>[Now]</hi> doth confeſſedly denote the ſtate of this Life, ſo the particle <hi>[Then]</hi> doth as plainly intimate any time or ſtate after this Life ended. And he might expreſs it ſo if it were properly and primarily meant of the Soul, in its Separation from the Body: As when he ſaid <hi>(Phil.</hi> 1.) <hi>I deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and be with Chriſt.</hi> Which [Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>with</hi> Chriſt] is confeſſedly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in reſpect of his <hi>Soul.</hi> Nor is it eaſie to conceive how his Soul's being with Chriſt after Death, ſhould be ſo much a better conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than any in this Life, if therein it had not perfection in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Love of Chriſt: For on Earth he had a great meaſure of them, and was daily tending for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards towards perfection, and was aſſured that nothing ſhould ſeparate him from the Love of Chriſt, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.)</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:179751:71"/>
               <p>Surely therefore a holy Soul will not want for knowledge when it has left the World. How can it be any thing leſs than perfectly light in the Lord, when it ſhall be perfectly and gloriouſly preſent with him? And who is able to tell us what a Joy and Bleſſedneſs this muſt be? If I could know my God and Saviour with ſuch a powerfull, ſpiritual and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting knowledge as ſome good Men have had on Earth, my heart ſhould be glad and my ſpirit rejoyce, though I were utterly deſpiſed in the World, and had not one hours health all the days of my Life; yet all their knowledge here was imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (as we have ſeen;) And how much better ſhall that ſtate be where all ſinfull imperfections ſhall be done away? If the Myſtery of Chriſt and Salvation by him, be ſuch a glorious thing <hi>that the Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven deſire to look into it,</hi> (1 Pet. 1.12.) O then what abundant matter
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:179751:71"/>of ſatisfaction and joy will it yield to all thoſe bleſſed Souls to whom it doth really and eternally belong? and to whom the worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it (with their intereſt in it) is fully diſcovered by the Spirit of Grace and Revelation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another privilege that holy Souls ſhall have after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence, is their Company.</p>
               <p>They ſhall then converſe with the beſt of Creatures, and ſuch as never offended their good God, I mean the Holy Angels: After Death they ſhall be (as it were) made Free of that Company, and ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Members of that Bleſſed So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety united in, and under, the ſame Head Chriſt Jeſus. Now (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) if they ſhould ſee but one of thoſe immortal Spirits ſtanding be fore them with his Crown of Glory, compaſſing them about with a Light brighter than that of the Sun, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to draw nigh unto them, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:179751:72"/>asking to joyn with them in the Praiſes of the great <hi>Jehovah;</hi> ſuch a ſight probably would more aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them than rejoyce them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſenſe of their ſinfulneſs might caſt a Damp upon their Hearts, and make them unfit for the heavenly employment: But it ſhall be otherwiſe with their Souls when they are fully conformed to their Maker's Will, and as free from ſin as the Angels of his preſence; for the Angels of Heaven and the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect, are Members of that happy Society which Divines uſe to call the Church Triumphant; and therefore are related to one another by a far nearer and nobler Relation than that of Fellow Creatures, of which the learned may conſult <hi>Polanus</hi> (in <hi>Syntag.</hi>) and <hi>H. Altingii Theol. Nov. problemat. p.</hi> 616. In a word, they are called in the Goſpel <hi>Their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> Math. 18.10.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:179751:72"/>
               <p>And we cannot think that thoſe bleſſed Spirits above that have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to them, and (by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment) took charge of them, and eſpecially, rejoyced at their Converſion, (<hi>Luke</hi> 15.10.) I ſay, we cannot think they will do any thing leſs than joyfully congratulate their ſafe Arrival at the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect purity and peace: and chiefly as it is the proper Fruit of the Will of God, and the purchaſe of his Chriſt. Surely the holy Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the beſt World, will not be ſtrange to Holy Souls when they come into it; nor are they like the fooliſh Hypocrites of the Earth that delight to ſhew themſelves proud and ſcornfull, and look with an evil eye upon the welfare of others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As I queſtion not a Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Converſe between the Angels of God, and the perfected Spirits of the Juſt, ſo hitherto I can as little doubt their knowledge of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:179751:73"/>one another and their ſatisfaction in each others Happineſs: (in their ſtate of Separation) at leaſt, and eſpecially, thoſe of them that were before more nearly related, and were wont to join together in God's Service and Praiſes here on Earth. For it was the deſign of Chriſt, to bring his People into a nearer Union with each other, as well as himſelf: [<hi>that they may be one as we are one,</hi> John 17.22.] And thoſe Arguments Divines bring for the Saints know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of one another after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, may ſeem almoſt as ſtrong for their Souls Acquaintance with one another, in their abſence from their Bodies. The Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the death of the faithfull ſays, that (therein) they are gathered to their Fathers (the holy Patriarchs and other their Religious Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours.) But they are not gathered to them in reſpect of their Bodies, therefore in reſpect of their Souls.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:179751:73"/>
               <p n="4">4. Holy Souls after Death ſhall be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>When ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Body, they are preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.8. And oh what a thing is this! 1. [To be with Chriſt] (in his ſpecial and blis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence, to know, love and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him fully, clearly, continually; as the ſame Apoſtle maketh it the Crown of all Comforts, <hi>To be for ever with the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.17.) Thus, I ſay, <hi>to be with</hi> Chriſt muſt needs be a matter of pureſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecteſt Joy to a Chriſtian's Soul. Oh that thou couldeſt fully underſtand (good Reader) the preciouſneſs of ſuch a privilege!</p>
               <p>But, Alas I want words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, much more a heart to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it: I am my ſelf too little a Chriſtian to tell thee the ſweetneſs of this Conſolation, to diſcover the depths of this pureſt River of the Water of Life. If the holy Apoſtle could ſolace himſelf in the hope of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:179751:74"/>having the Company of his converts at <hi>Rome;</hi> If the Lord Chancellour of <hi>England</hi> (in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th.) was ſo much deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſee in <hi>London</hi> the <hi>Florentine</hi> Merchant that (in ſome difficult caſes) had befriended him beyond Sea; (the expreſſions of whoſe joy and gratitude were ſo memorable, that the Learned Dr. <hi>Hakwell,</hi> thought good to record them, in his Apology of God's power and providence;) If the Hearts of the weak have gathered ſtrength, and revived to admiration at the coming of ſome eminent unexpected Friends: (though theſe were but dying Duſt, and had not any degree of comfort abſolutely at their command:) How unſpeakably then muſt a gracious Soul be refreſhed, and moſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively ſatisfied, by the preſence and favour of that immortal Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty who ſuffered Death, and the Curſe to make it happy?</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:179751:74"/>
               <p>Surely it muſt needs be an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefit to be in the happieſt manner, <hi>preſent with him</hi> who is the King of Glory, the Conſolation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the joy of Angels, and the Saviour of the World.</p>
               <p>This therefore, as he was a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, was his great deſire for his People, <hi>That they might be with him where he is,</hi> John 17.24. The joy of which we may a little gueſs at by the things that ſhall accompany this their <hi>Preſence</hi> with him.</p>
               <p>As (1.) a full Deliverance from all Doubts and Fears, and all things that may cauſe, or occaſion them. Here how hard a thing was it for them to get an aſſurance of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, and Salvation by him? and when they had it, t'was no eaſie matter to maintain and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: yea the beſt on Earth are not ſo privileged, but that if they be not carefull and watchfull over them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they may fall into ſuch ſins
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:179751:75"/>as may darken all their evidences for Heaven, and deprive them of the Joy of their Salvation. It was <hi>David</hi>'s caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. But when once their Souls come to dwell with Chriſt, then they ſhall be ever ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from all poſſibility of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about their ſpiritual and eternal welfare: no ſuch ſad miſt can cloud that Soul which lives under the Rayes of the Sun of Righteouſneſs: Here as they may have aſſurance, ſo they may looſe it again. But to be with Chriſt is far better, in that reſpect: and they then Reſt from their Labours (from all that may be tedious and tireſome unto them,) <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Preſence</hi> with the Lord (in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſenſe) will ſet them free from all manner of cares: not only from diſorderly and diſtruſtfull cares, but alſo from all natural, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and prudential cares, which their preſent ſtate doth expoſe them
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:179751:75"/>to: And the reaſon is plain, becauſe then their Souls are above all wants and neceſſities: They want not for Monies when they are fully poſſeſt of the riches of Chriſt; They want for no Friendſhip and good Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, when they are happily joyned to the whole Family of Heaven. They take no care for Food or Sleep, when they enjoy him who is the Bread of Life, and partake of that eternal Reſt which he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In a word; Then they ſhall be freed from taking any care about doing their Duty, and pleaſing their God: For the <hi>Difficulty</hi> of Duty will then be over, and the <hi>Comfort</hi> of it only ſhall remain. When they thus dwell with the holy one, they ſhall be fully framed to his holy Will. To love God in perfection, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, (without which Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf cannot make us happy.) Theſe things (I ſay) willbe as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:179751:76"/>and eaſie to holy Souls after death, as it is to a thirſty man to drink, or to the eye to behold the deſired Light; There being no ſin then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in them, to alienate and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trange them from their gracious God, (as hath been already proved.)</p>
               <p>And as their Being with Chriſt ſecureth them from all Trouble, ſo it ſhall afford them the trueſt and ſtrongeſt Conſolation: and that on theſe following grounds. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhall then ſee Chriſt to be their Own for ever: And in all their knowledge of him they ſhall know him to be <hi>Theirs.</hi> Propriety is in it ſelf a pleaſant thing: with what content do Men many times ſpeak even of thoſe outward (inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient) comforts which they can truly call <hi>their own. My</hi> Mony and <hi>my</hi> Lands, <hi>my</hi> Relations and <hi>my</hi> Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do uſually ſound with an <hi>Accent</hi> of Pleaſure. O what bleſſed Delight then, muſt a pious
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:179751:76"/>Soul be elevated with, when it dwells with Chriſt in a better World? What Triumphant exultation will it be filled with, when it can ſay (with full aſſurance) <hi>My</hi> Rock and <hi>my</hi> Refuge, <hi>my</hi> Lord and <hi>my</hi> King, <hi>my</hi> God and <hi>my</hi> Saviour, <hi>my</hi> great High Prieſt and <hi>my</hi> Redeemer!</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. When they are with Chriſt (in the ſenſe aforeſaid) they ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the eternal Treaſure, and know (perfectly) <hi>the Love of Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge,</hi> Eph. 3.19. The very <hi>Being</hi> with him, neceſſarily implies the enjoying of his Love, (as the <hi>Departing</hi> from him, imports the want of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.) And how great a Happineſs muſt that be? And though I cannot comprehend it, yet I may fitly take occaſion to conſider it: and it ſhall be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the following Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:179751:77"/>
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>Shewing the Greatneſs of the Love of Chriſt, which the Souls of his People ſhall enjoy after Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIthout this, my ſmall Book would be too ſmall, and would ſpeak me guilty of too great an overſight to be handſomly excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. For how ſhould I make good its Title Page, of the Joy of Juſt Mens Souls after Death, if I ſhould not treat of that Love of his, which ſhall ſurely be their Glory and Joy?</p>
               <p>And though it may be ſomewhat difficult to reſolve in what method to diſcourſe of his unmeaſurable Love, yet I think the main of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns me to ſay, may be reduced to theſe two Heads.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:179751:77"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What Chriſt is, in Himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>What he hath done and ſuffered for Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, let us conſider (for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) <hi>what Chriſt is in himſelf.</hi> For, as it was ſaid of old, as the Man is, ſuch is his Strength; ſo we may ſay herein, as the Perſon is, ſuch is his Love; the more excellent any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, the more excellent and valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able is his Kindneſs, in what way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be expreſſed towards his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours. It were a greater matter for one that is a King, to hazard his Health for the good of any People, than for an ordinary Perſon to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his Life for them.</p>
               <p>Now on this account, the Love of Chriſt towards Sinners, muſt needs be worthy of everlaſting Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe he was a Perſon of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite excellency, the Eternal Son of God, of the ſame ſubſtance with his
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:179751:78"/>heavenly Father.] Reader, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, Hold faſt this Principle, and part not with it as thou loveſt the life of thy precious Soul. For the contrary opinion is not only an errour, but ſuch an errour as ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth at the very heart of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and overthrows the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Faith. 'Tis not my preſent Deſign to prove this at large, (yet ſomething ſhall be ſaid of it in due place.) And (by the way) we may perceive how neceſſary the Knowledge of it is, by conſidering that of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.13. He asked his Diſciples, <hi>Whom do Men ſay that I the Son of Man am:</hi> q. d. They are very well ſatisfied that I am indeed the Son of Man, true and very Man (as really as any of you is;) But what do they think of my Perſon? Do they take me to be a <hi>Humane</hi> Perſon, and ſo no more than a Man, or the Son of Man? To which the Diſciples an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:179751:78"/>
                  <hi>Some ſay, Thou art John the Baptiſt, ſome Elias,</hi> &amp;c. (Perſons very eminent, and as great in God's account as any of the Sons of Men.) But yet they did not therein think highly enough of him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. He asked his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>Whom ſay ye that I am?</hi> To which <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the reſt, giveth anſwer ſaying, <hi>Thou art Chriſt, the Son of the living God,</hi> verſ. 16. which Anſwer <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo well appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of, that he pronounced him bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. and intimated this Truth to be the Rock on which the Church is built: and aſſureth him, that againſt it the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>And now that [his being the Son of the living God] (which he took to himſelf ſo apparently) is meant of being his <hi>Son</hi> properly, by eternal and unſpeakable Generation, of the ſame ſubſtance with his Father. This (I ſay) is now to be cleared and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:179751:79"/>confirmed, and it may be ſo from thoſe Scriptures wherein he is called, <hi>The Son of the Father,</hi> 2 John 3. <hi>His own Son,</hi> Rom. 8. <hi>His only begotten Son,</hi> John 3. <hi>who had Glory with the Father before the World was,</hi> Joh. 17.5. <hi>who thought it no Robbery to be</hi> (or declare himſelf to be) <hi>equal with God,</hi> (viz. God the Father) <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. Titles certainly too high for any mere Creature (whatever <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> ſuggeſt to the contrary.) The <hi>Jews</hi> ſuppoſed him guilty of Blaſphemy, becauſe he being a Man, made himſelf God (that is, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf ſo to be) which they did not charge him with, on any other ground than his owning himſelf to be the Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 5.18.10.33. compared with <hi>Mark</hi> 14, 61, 64.</p>
               <p>And if our Saviour had not been the Son of God in ſuch a ſenſe as imported him to be true and very God (as the <hi>Jews</hi> conceived him to mean,) there is no doubt but he
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:179751:79"/>would have ſhewed them their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, yea quickly too, and have diſowned that Title (in the ſenſe that they took it) being Lowly in Heart, and filled with the higheſt Zeal for his Father's Glory.</p>
               <p>And that he was not called the Son of God, upon the account of his miraculous conception, or any privileges that a meer Creature may partake of (as too many would perſwade us) may be eaſily manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on theſe two grounds 1 Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was the Son of God before theſe things could be ſaid of him. As (in the fullneſs of time) he came of the Lineage of <hi>David,</hi> according to the Fleſh, and was called the Son of <hi>David:</hi> So before his Incarnation, he was <hi>David</hi>'s Lord. <hi>David in Spirit called him Lord,</hi> Mat. 22.43. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. Surely therefore he was a Perſon in <hi>David</hi>'s time: And what Perſon was he then? Surely the ſame that now he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:179751:80"/>is, even the Son of God: The ſame in all times paſt, preſent, and to come, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and forever,</hi> H. 13. Nor do I yet find that the <hi>Socinians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ever were ſo ſenſeleſs as to ſay, that Chriſt was the Son of Man, or one of the Angels, in <hi>David</hi>'s time. (And if then he were not a Humane Perſon, nor an Angelical Perſon: what remains but that he was a <hi>Divine</hi> Perſon at that time, (&amp; therefore at all times.) In a word, he was then ſuch a Son as the ſame Kingly Prophet calls upon Men to <hi>truſt</hi> in, and calls them bleſſed that do ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12. and therefore God the Son, of the ſame ſubſtance with his Father (and ſo above the rank of meer creatures, for to truſt in a meer crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is ſo far from bleſſedneſs that it is in it ſelf an accurſed thing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such things are ſaid of Chriſt, the Son of God as no temporal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, privileges, or qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:179751:80"/>can poſſibly entitle him to: as, To have his outgoings from everlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>Micha</hi> 5.2. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.6. To be the Firſt and the Laſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. To have all things conſiſt in him (or by him) <hi>Col.</hi> 1. To have all things created by him, and for him, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. Not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on thoſe places where he is called God abſolutely, and ſolemnly, ſee <hi>John</hi> 20.28. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Unto the Son he ſaith, Thy Throne O God is for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any can convince me, that all this will not prove Chriſt to be the Son of God, in a higher ſenſe and manner than any temporal privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or created excellencies can make him to be, they then may have hope enough to make me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that my Right Hand is my Left, or any other piece of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt Non-ſenſe, that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Right Reaſon can impoſe upon me. Yet it being a matter
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:179751:81"/>above the reach of natural Reaſon, I muſt ſay, (with him in the Goſpel) <hi>Lord I believe, Help thou my unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi> They that would ſee more on this great ſubject, may conſult <hi>Steg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-photin Refut. Diſp.</hi> 5. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 7. <hi>Jacobi ad part. Def. Fidei.</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the acute <hi>Thalyaeus</hi> in <hi>Anat. Samoſat. quaeſt.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>And whereas ſome do much urge <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.35. to prove that Chriſt was the Son of God, by reaſon of his miraculous Conception, becauſe 'tis immediately added. <hi>[Wherefore alſo that holy thing that ſhall be Born of Thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.]</hi> This I ſay, will not ſerve their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: And if from hence they could make ſuch a knot as we could not untie, yet that would not make the matter e're the <hi>clearer</hi> on <hi>their</hi> ſide. And whether we can ſearch the depth of that ſacred Text or no, yet we may ſoon be perſwaded that this his miraculous conception was
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:179751:81"/>not the chief reaſon of his being, or being called, the Son of God. For if ſo, he muſt have been the <hi>Son of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>this</hi> work is peculiarly aſcribed to <hi>him</hi> in the foregoing verſe. <hi>But Chriſt,</hi> we are told, <hi>is the Son of the Father,</hi> John 2.3. and the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Son,</hi> Gal. 4.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Chriſt was the Son of God, on account of his miraculous concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then he began to be ſo when that began: But 'tis not ſo (certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) For he was the Son of God long before, and was ſo called, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7.12. and he had Glory with his Father before the World was, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.5.</p>
               <p>He was therefore the Eternal Son of the Father (as our Church ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) on account of an eternal and unſpeakable Generation. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Perſon of infinite Dignity, his Love muſt needs be of infinite value; ſo that the utmoſt conceivable kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:179751:82"/>of all the Angels in Heaven, (if they were as many as the drops in the Sea, and the Sands on the Shore) would be utterly inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in compariſon of <hi>His,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Underſtandings of mortal Men, almoſt as far as it doth their Deſervings, (which by the next Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may farther appear.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>Diſcovering the Greatneſs of Chriſt's Love, in what he did, and ſuffered for Sinners.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That the ſenſe of the love of Chriſt, will be the ſpecial matter of the joy of Juſt Mens Souls after Death, will eaſily be granted, and may in its place be farther proved: At pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:179751:82"/>I think it my Duty, and full enough to my purpoſe, to ſet forth the greatneſs of his Love, in the great things that he did and ſuffered for Sinners ſake. And firſt, I may fitly inſtance in <hi>his</hi> taking our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into unity with his own Divine Perſon, ſo as to become true and <hi>very</hi> Man, like unto us, <hi>Sin</hi> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. If St. <hi>John</hi> ſo much admired that ſuch as we ſhould be called the Sons of God (by Adoption,) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what manner of Love is this?</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1. How then may we wonder at that <hi>Love</hi> that moved the Son of God from Everlaſting, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Son of <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>Time?</hi> What a height of kindneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion was that which moved the moſt High and Holy one to ſtoop ſo low for our ſakes and Salvation? Sure the utmoſt kindneſs that the beſt of Creatures can have towards us, in compariſon of this Love of Chriſt, is but as a drop to the Sea,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:179751:83"/>or as a Mote in the Sun to the whole frame of Nature.</p>
               <p>For let us but think with our ſelves what a wondrous thing it was that the Son of God ſhould vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to take our Nature on him, and be made in the likeneſs of ſinfull Fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. well may we ſay in this as the Pſalmiſt doth, <hi>Lord, what is Man that thou art mindfull of him?</hi> For the Nature of Man that is corrupt with ſin, and ſubject to the darkneſs of the Grave, what is this, (I ſay) to him who is the Light of the City of God, and had Glory with the Father before the World was, <hi>John</hi> 17.5. Thus there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to aſſume our Nature, might ſeem a matter infinitely <hi>below</hi> him, but that his love thought <hi>nothing</hi> ſo. And as he took Humane Nature to himſelf, ſo in it he did thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things that expreſſed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his <hi>Love</hi> towards Men, and the care he took of their eternal
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:179751:83"/>Salvation. <hi>He came into the World to ſave Sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. He went about doing good, preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt abſolute uncontrolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miracles for Confirmation of his holy Doctrine, leading them in the way to Heaven by his own bleſſed example, bearing patiently the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Slanders, and ſuffering the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions of Sinners againſt himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.3. Overcoming daily their evil with good, and inviting them to himſelf to come unto him, that they might have Life. And the eminency of his Love and Goodneſs, will be eſpecially viſible in the evils that he ſuffered, and voluntarily expoſed himſelf to for the ſake of Sinners; which, being compared with the excellency and innocency of his Perſon, will eaſily appear to exceed the moſt enlarged thoughts of Men and Angels. As to this therefore, I muſt ſay with the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:179751:84"/>
                  <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> And as it was ſaid of old, <hi>who hath declared his Generation?</hi> So I may (as juſtly) who can declare his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and Paſſion, and that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Depth of Divine Love that was diſcovered therein?</p>
               <p>That he whom the Heaven of Heavens could not contain, and of whom they borrow their Brightneſs and Glory, ſhould be laid in a Manger, and live in Meanneſs and Obſcurity; That He who is <hi>Rich</hi> from all Eternity ſhould in time become poor for our Sakes; That He who was the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Author and Maintainer <hi>of the Water of Life</hi> (Rev. 22.1.) ſhould Himſelf be ſubject to Wearineſs and Thirſt, and be fain to refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſo weak a Cordial as the Water of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well (John 4.) That He whom the Higheſt Angels worſhipped ſhould be abuſed by the baſeſt Men, be reviled and ſcorn'd,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:179751:84"/>buffeted and ſpitted on, and (at laſt) be Crucified between two Malefactours, (as if he had been the worſt of the Three) That He who was purer than all the created In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the high and holy Place, ſhould ſuffer himſelf to be tempted to Sin, and bear Day by Day, the vileſt Aſſaults of the unclean Spirit: (<hi>Math.</hi> 4.) That He who uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things by the word of his power, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.) ſhould be weak and faint, and in the midſt of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, give up the Ghoſt: That He who was the Heir of all things, and the Son of the Bleſſed, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all Comforts, and cry out upon the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and (in a word) fall under Condemnation, and be made a Curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. Wonder, Chriſtian Reader, wonder evermore at that Superlative Love which moved him to do, and ſuffer ſuch marvellous things for ſuch as
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:179751:85"/>we. Methinks our Hearts ſhould be mightily affected with it, and our whole Souls be ſwallowed up as it were in this bleſſed and boundleſs Ocean; And becauſe we can know but little of it whilſt we live, let us be content to dye, that our Souls may know it better; For certainly the perfect Knowledge and Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this tranſcendent Love of Chriſt, muſt needs be no leſs than Bleſſedneſs indeed. If the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (after the Dedication of the Houſe of God) went away ſo glad and merry in heart for the Goodneſs that the Lord had ſhewed them therein, (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.10.) If they had ſo much comfort in their Souls when Providence had delivered them from the ſorrows of their Captivity, and made them ſit in peace under their own Vines; <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.17. If the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men rejoyced ſo exceedingly when they ſaw but our Saviour's Star ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? <hi>Math.</hi> 2.10. O then what
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:179751:85"/>bleſſed Joy may we conceive to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs thoſe happy Souls, that partake of the ſweeteſt Influences of that Sun of Righteouſneſs, and enjoy thoſe Rivers of ſacred pleaſures that flow from his everlaſting Love? (being perfected at the ſame time in their Love towards him) This muſt needs be far better than the beſt condition here; and how much better thou ſhalt know, Chriſtian Reader, at the fitteſt Seaſon, in a far better manner than I am able to tell thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:179751:86"/>
               <head>SECT. XV. <hi>Being other Brief Improvements of the Point.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS Truth will truly ſerve for other good purpoſes, beſides thoſe already mentioned: and in the next place it may aſſure us of the comfortableneſs of a Chriſtian Life The Enemies of Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and wicked men, inſtead of Reaſons againſt it do rather deal in Reproaches and Slanders: And there's ſcarcely a greater reproach caſt on it by the Men of the World than the unpleaſantneſs of it (as they imagine) and the oppoſition they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to carry againſt Mens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Comfort and Content. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:179751:86"/>they confeſs, is many times (like Fire) a good Servant (as we uſe to ſay) and therefore they think good (it may be) to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, and make a profeſſion of it for their Credit ſake, or other earthly Ends: But in the mean time they are loth to account it a good Maſter: For if they came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of it, and be ruled by it in their general Courſe, they think it would make them melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and robb them of the very Joy of their Lives. But aſſuredly there is no more reaſon why we ſhould be aſraid of Piety for the cauſeleſs Cenſures of ungodly Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, than why we ſhould deſpiſe the Light of the Sun for a mad Man's mocking and railing at it.</p>
               <p>Let men but try the good way in truth, and walk uprightly in it, and then (my Life upon it) it ſhall not (in the main) make them ſad: It ſhall much rather make them
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:179751:87"/>glad; yea it ſhall one day be the Joy of their Hearts to remember that they walked therein, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>This is our rejoycing, the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Conſciences, that in Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and godly Sincerity, we have had our Converſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the reaſon of it may in part be ſeen from hence; for the good Way ſhall have a good End, and bring them that walk in it to a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py State in ſpight of all that Death can do; yea after it has done its worſt upon them. When they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this Life, they ſhall be with Chriſt which is far better, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We may here inform our ſelves of the Nature of thoſe Troubles that come upon good Chriſtians in this Life, <hi>viz.</hi> That they are but Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and not Curſes: Trials of Grace and mercifull Viſitations, not Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances in the leaſt Degree, or any Effects of deſtructive wrath; for ſurely that mercifull Father that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:179751:87"/>will make them ſo happy after Death doth not mean any miſchief to them, in the Afflictions he layeth on them in this preſent Life: But will make all things work together for good unto them that love him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may encourage Chriſtians in their Spiritual Warfare, and make them to run with patience the Race that is ſet before them. How ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly ſhould they now ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, ſince they ſhall ſhortly be more than Conquerours through him that loved them? what Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties ſhould make them weary of well doing, ſince they ſhall ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and ſo ſpeedily enter upon the Eternal Reſt?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let Chriſtians ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this point and endeavour by Prayer and Meditation, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good means to get their Hearts more affected with this Happineſs that is ſo near at hand. And to this end compare we the Joy of Juſt
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:179751:88"/>Mens Souls made perfect, with other matters of Conſolation, that the Scripture offers unto our thoughts; O what gladneſs would it have put into the Heart of a pious Chriſtian, to have ſeen the Saviour of the World in the Temple, to have heard him preach the Doctrine of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpeak as never Man ſpake? To have ſeen the Multitudes that were miraculouſly fed, and the Dead that were raiſed by him? To have ſeen him invite poor Sinners to himſelf (ſtanding in the moſt ſolemn Day of the Feſtival) and crying with a loud Voice, <hi>whoſoever is a-thirſt let him come unto me and drink;</hi> eſpecially if at the ſame time he could have known his need of him, and intereſt in him? And what a Joy would it have been to have ſeen him (after his Conqueſt over Death) aſcending to the high and holy Place? To have ſtood among the Celeſtial
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:179751:88"/>Orbs, to behold how he paſſed through the Regions of the Air, how dark the brighteſt Stars were made by the preſence of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Glory? But chiefly, what a thing would it have been, to have ſeen the <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus</hi> at his <hi>Entrance</hi> into the Heaven of Heavens? To have ſeen the Everlaſting Doors ſet open for that <hi>King</hi> of Glory to enter in? together with that unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble welcome which he then recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all the Heavenly Hierarchy, Angels and Archangels, Cherubins and Seraphins, (all the innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Armies of immortal Spirits) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating his incomparable Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries over Sin, the Devil and Death, offering up their praiſes to him, and caſting all their Crowns before him? How joyfull a thing may we well conceive this would have been, or rather joyfull beyond all our preſent conceptions? And yet I think we may eaſily believe that the perfected
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:179751:89"/>Spirits of the Juſt do enjoy more comfort than all this could amount to; for though in ſuch Caſes a Godly Man's Eye would in a great Meaſure affect his Soul, yet while his Soul is ſinfull, 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be ſo perfectly joyfull as when it is freed from all Sin; And while Sin is in it ſelf Enmity againſt God, it abiding in us muſt needs be an Enemy to our Comforts, and withhold (in ſome meaſure) Good things from us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:179751:89"/>
               <head>SECT. XVI. <hi>Being a farther Improvement of the Doctrine aforeſaid, as an Antidote againſt the fear of Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE that dwells in a World where Dying is ſo much in faſhion, ſhould be (one would think) very inquiſitive after ſomething (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be found) that may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him againſt that fatal ſtroke which he has ſo little hopes of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping; nor can I apprehend how any Man ſhould be able to lead a truly comfortable Life, that is not above the fears of Death, in ſome good meaſure; becauſe there is no Place or Caſe, no Company or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, no Day nor Hour wherein
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:179751:90"/>it may not overtake him (for ought he knows to the contrary.) And though what I am now to add can be but little comfort to the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ungodly World (becauſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion will comfort none whom it doth not rule) yet to the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Chriſtian I hope it may afford even ſtrong conſolation; For what more effectual Armor againſt the fears of Death can be ſhewed to ſuch a one (or be wiſhed by him) than this Truth before us? [That Death it ſelf ſhall be his advantage, and prove a Friend unto his Soul.] If a Man have an Antipathy againſt Bleeding, (ſo as to ſaint almoſt at the very thought of it) yet he that can prove that it is neceſſary for him as a means againſt thoſe difficult and dangerous diſtempers that he feels or fears (and can demonſtrate the ſafety of it alſo) may thereby reconcile him to it, and make him not only content, but glad alſo, to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:179751:90"/>part with a little of his Blood. Much more may a Godly Chriſtian be content to part with his Life (when God calls for it,) while his Faith and his Reaſon is really ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, (by the word of truth) that his Death ſhall be ſafe and gainfull, and that his Lord and Saviour will be better to his Soul than the Life of his Body, and all created com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts whatſoever. For a wicked Man to be afraid of dying is no wonder at all, nor no Abſurdity neither: well may he fear Death that ſhall feel Damnation after it, if he dye in the State he is yet in; but for a Religious Perſon, that placeth his Happineſs in God through Chriſt, and deſires nothing more than to be fitter to ſerve and enjoy him: For ſuch a one to be afraid of dying, O what pity is it? I do not ſay 'tis ſtrange: For alas, it is but too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the beſt: (Many are now of a fearfull Heart, that ſhall ſtand
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:179751:91"/>without Fear at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;) but I may ſafely ſay that ſuch Fears, in ſuch Perſons, are very needleſs and ſtrangely unreaſonable. As yet I know nothing that a good Chriſtian is leſs concern'd to fear than dying: For when he is <hi>abſent from the Body, he ſhall be preſent with the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.8. that is, in a more excellent manner than he was or could be, in this mortal Life, in a State far better, as 'tis expreſſed elſewhere (<hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23.) God hath often ſaid by his Prophets, <hi>Fear not,</hi> and in <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.10. He urged it to his Servant, with the Reaſon of it: [Fear not for I am with thee: Be not diſmayed for I am thy God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] Now if any ſhuld ſay this may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them perhaps from fearing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Evils, but not from fearing Death, I wou'd then demand the Reaſon of his Speech, and can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf that he cannot ſhew any Reaſon, truly ſo called, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:179751:91"/>of it; And I need ſay no more to confute him therein, than to tell him that God is the God of his People, as truly, and as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably at a dying Hour as at any other time; and that Death ſhall not ſeparate them from the Love of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38.</p>
               <p>But poſſibly it may be expected that I ſhould anſwer ſome objections; which alſo, with God's Aſſiſtance I ſhall endeavour to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. When you have ſaid all you can, yet (ſay ſome) we know very well, that Dying is a Hard word, and a Harder thing: and hath ſuch Difficulties accompanying it, as are puzling and unpleaſing to the moſt of Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What it may be to the <hi>moſt,</hi> is little to my purpoſe to enquire of: For 'tis not <hi>moſt</hi> Men but <hi>good</hi> and <hi>upright</hi> Chriſtians that here I ſpeak of. And that Dying is ſo hard a thing to ſuch perſons, I think I am not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:179751:92"/>to believe: 'Tis confeſſed it may ſeem ſo unto them, but it is not ſo indeed; for the Difficulties are more fancifull than real. And when they are moſt troubled at the thoughts of Death, yet (in that Caſe) it is not Dying it ſelf, but Snning and Doubting, that is the cauſe of their Diſtreſs: which as to the weakeſt true Chriſtian they are pardoned for Chriſt's Sake, ſo at Death there is an end of them. (See before, Sect. 12.) Chriſt's Death for them has taken away the Sting of Death, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56, 57.) So that they have more cauſe to be afraid of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, than of Dying: For in Life they are liable to variety of Troubles, and may often be in heavineſs through manifold Temptations: But in Dying, they are ſubject to none of them. From thence forth their Souls ſhall never ſee one evil Hour. <hi>They that dye in the Lord are bleſſed from thence forth, and they reſt from their Labours,</hi> Rev. 14.13.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:179751:92"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But at a dying Hour we may expect <hi>Satan</hi>'s fierceſt Aſſaults, and ſtrongeſt Temptations: For he is never more apt to aſſail us than when we are at the weakeſt; (as ſome report of the Learned and Pious Mr. <hi>Pemble,</hi> that when he lay on his Death-bed, the wicked one managed his ſubtileſt Suggeſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, even in way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to baffle his Faith in the Bleſſed Jeſus, to keep his Soul from reſting on that Rock of Salvation.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This needs not to trouble any true hearted Chriſtian: For (firſt,) he cannot conclude it ſhall therefore be his own caſe; or that his laſt Hour ſhall be, in any ſad ſenſe, an Hour of Temptation. God deals very variouſly with his People, and ordereth all their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs according to the Methods of his own moſt mercifull Will and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Mr. <hi>Pemble,</hi> and others, had manifold Temptations in their latter
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:179751:93"/>Hours; Mr. <hi>Holland, Molinaeus,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Bolton,</hi> and multitudes more had their Hearts then filled with Heaven's Peace; and though <hi>Satan</hi> wants not malice, or knowledge, to take advantage of their weakneſſes, and to oppoſe them with his fiery Darts when he ſees them leaſt able to reſiſt; yet we are ſure his Power is limited, ſo that he cannot give them one Minutes diſturbance more than God is pleaſed to permit, <hi>whoſe mercy,</hi> we are told, <hi>is to everlaſting upon them that fear him,</hi> (Pſal. 103.17.) and therefore ſhall not be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from them by all the Power of Hell. How well would they be ſatisfied if ſome of their beſt friends (whoſe kindneſs they have moſt experienced) had a power given them to order all circumſtances that concern their Death? Behold the matter is much ſafer than ſo, and all their Affairs in a better hand. Sure I am, the trueſt Affection, and
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:179751:93"/>heartieſt Love of the moſt compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Parent upon Earth is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and vanity to the tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that Great High Prieſt, and gracious Saviour with whom they have to do. Nor would he be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Shepherd of their Souls (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.) if he did not mean to take care of them accordingly, and help them in their greateſt need.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 3. But the mere Abſence of the Soul from its Body, may ſeem to make its condition ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable; for Philoſophers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly write of the Deſire it hath to the Body, and a late Metaphyſical Pen has laid it down as a Theorem <hi>[Deſiderat Anima ſeparata iterum cum corpore conjngi] i.e.</hi> The ſeparated Soul deſires to be united to its Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to this, I think that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> may fitly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, <hi>Take heed leſt any man ſpoyle you through Philoſophy and vain Deceit:</hi> For indeed, Some things
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:179751:94"/>that go under that Name are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently vain and deceitfull. And as to this. [the Soul's deſire to be united to the Body again] if meant of the Souls of the Juſt, to me ſeemeth no excellent Notion; nor can I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how men ſhould know it if it were ſo indeed. Their Arguments for it I am not ſatisfied in, and I hope it is excuſable if I venture to urge one or two againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If a good Chriſtian's Soul, when abſent from the Body, doth actually and properly deſire to be joyned to it, (as a ſick man deſireth health, or a Priſoner Liberty) then whilſt ſeparate, it muſt wiſh to be in another condition; as the Sick wiſheth his health. But the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Soul of a good Chriſtian doth not wiſh it ſelf at that time any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condition: for being perfectly <hi>ſanctified,</hi> it is perfectly <hi>ſatisfied</hi> in the Will of God, who crowneth it with his loving kindneſs, and is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:179751:94"/>unto it than the Body, and all the comforts here below.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If ſuch a Soul thus deſireth to be in the Body; then, the Being in the Body ſeems to it a better and more deſirable State, but that it doth not, nor cannot without Deluſion; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>to depart and be with Chriſt is far better,</hi> Philip. 1. And if in any ſenſe it deſires to be joyned to its Body, yet it deſires this only in God's appointed time, for the reaſon afore given.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 4. But may it not grieve a Man to think of leaving his old Friends and Acquaintance, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into that World and State which he never ſaw, nor ever ſpake with any that did?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doubtleſs this is that which lyeth hid in the hearts of many, though they ſpeak not to any ſuch purpoſe: And an evil Heart of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief may be much moved by it. But how little cauſe a Godly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:179751:95"/>hath to be unwilling to dye on this Account, a few words may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to make manifeſt. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that is ſuch indeed hath his Will, in ſome good meaſure, reſigned up to his God, whoſe Will is, that He and his Friends ſhould not dwell always together in this World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Friends that he leaveth at Death, are but fellow Creatures, and ſinfull ones too; ſuch Friends as may afflict him, as well as comfort him; in a word, ſuch as may hinder, as well as help in the way towards Heaven. (Nor can their greateſt Friendſhip be firm and conſtant to him any farther than God's Favour doth make it ſo, nor do them any good without his good providence.) But by Death, the Sanctified Soul is tranſlated into a far better condition, to enjoy that moſt gracious glorious God, who was his firſt and beſt Friend; to whoſe undeſerved good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he was abſolutely beholding for
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:179751:95"/>all the kindneſs that ever any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhew'd him; In ſhort, that bleſſed God to whom all Nations, (as the Prophet ſpeaks,) are as nothing and vanity; that God whoſe Name alone is excellent, and his Glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Heavens; whoſe Power is Omnipotency, whoſe Time is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whoſe Bounty is unſpeakable, and whoſe Benignity is better than Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. And touching the other part of the Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> [the Strangeneſs of the State that the Soul doth enter upon] nothing but groſs infidelity can make it ſeem of any weight. For (1.) <hi>Strangeneſs</hi> in it ſelf hath no harm in it: When the man that was born blind had Sight given him by Our Saviour, it was doubtleſs a <hi>Strange</hi> thing to him to perceive the Light which he never did before, nor could have any Ideas of: yet the change was not grievous but joyous unto him. How much more muſt it be ſo with that bleſſed Change
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:179751:96"/>(to a Bleſſedneſs that changeth not) which a gracious Soul ſhall find after Death? And (2.) as to ſuch a <hi>Strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> as conſiſteth in <hi>unacquaintedneſs;</hi> I take it to be a ſtrange Fancy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ground at all in Scripture or Reaſon: yea the contrary ſeems very evident from Scripture. For as to their God the Caſe is clear; in their abſence from the Body they are preſent with the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. And that it is meant of a more ſpecial and comfortable preſence with him than before they had, may eaſily be gathered from the Apoſtle's Scope in that place; and is partly proved in a foregoing Section, where that moſt comfortable Text is inſiſted on. And how can they but have a nearer Communion with him, when they are freed from Ignorance and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and all thoſe things that are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive in his Sight?</p>
               <p>And concerning the Creatures alſo, I humbly conceive that the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:179751:96"/>Souls of ſuch Perſons do not want for Acquaintance with them: How can we imagine that thoſe Holy Angels ſhould deſire to be ſtrange to thoſe Souls in another World, that delighted to do them good in this World, and rejoyced in their Grace and Repentance? <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. Will thoſe heavenly Inhabitants chuſe to be at a Diſtance with them, when they are moſt perfectly united to their glorious Lord and Head, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous? This let them believe that can: for my part I hate the Thoughts of ſo groſs a Soleciſm. And I ſee no cauſe to doubt of the ſpiritual Communion and Converſe of Holy Souls with each other, in this their State of Separation; The knowing one another can be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience when they are complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Grace, and perfected in Love. That <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> are found in the perfected Spirits of the Juſt, is confeſſed by all that believe them to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:179751:97"/>ſuch, and to partake of any Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs after Death: And how can theſe Affections more properly be exerciſed among them, than in <hi>Rejoycing</hi> at each others Happineſs? And how can <hi>that</hi> be without the Knowledge of each other, and of their happy State? And to this I ſhall only add the poſition of the Learned <hi>Macco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius. Communicant Animae Separatae, &amp;c.</hi> Separated Souls do communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their minds to one another. <hi>De Anima Sep. Cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 5. But (ſay ſome) it is not Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> Dying that we are ſo unwilling of. Alas, we are ſo haunted with horrible Temptations, and our Faith and Hope are ſo ſadly ſhaken therewith, that we fear leſt we ſhould dye in Deſpair: which alſo we are the more amazed at, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are told that Deſpair is a moſt horrid Sin, ſuch as ſpoileth all at once (as we ſay) and ſtops up (as it were) the current of God's Mercy towards us.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:179751:97"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection I cannot but think fit to deal with; and I am the more willing to do ſo for the Satisfaction of thoſe, whoſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Friends may have dyed in Doubts and Fears, (and with no Appearance of comfort:) For which end I lay down the enſuing Aſſertions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſuch a caſe is not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the State of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Though the bright Morning Star (Chriſt ſo called) be truly riſen upon any Perſon, and hath imparted to him the Light of Life, yet that doth not make it impoſſible for his Sun to ſet in a Cloud; for the Word of God ſays nothing to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Though he therein promiſeth his Servants everlaſting Joy after Death, yet he promiſed not that they ſhould have Joy the Minute, or Hour before they dye. And when <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>there is one Event to the Righteous and to the Wicked</hi> (as to outwards he meaneth) <hi>Ecl.</hi> 9.2. I
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:179751:98"/>cannot fanſie, why any uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Circumſtances about Death ſhould ſeem to be excepted. Our Bleſſed Lord himſelf (in compariſon of whoſe Holineſs the Heaven of Heavens is but unclean) departed this Life in the Depths of Sorrow, and cryed with a loud voice, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Math. 27.46.50. Which being inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, gave ſome ſatisfaction to a Learned and worthy Divine, when (in his laſt Sickneſs) he asked his Friend, what that man might think of the State of his Soul that is juſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying, and can find no comfort in his God? Mr. <hi>Rob. Bolton</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a very Religious Gentlewoman, who in her latter Hours was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with many Sorrows, and, to appearance, dyed in them (ſhewing little or no Sign of any comfort in her Soul.) But that judicious Man of God did not think the worſe of her State, or queſtion her Salvation:
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:179751:98"/>but rather ſuppoſed that ſad Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of her God to be in Judgment to thoſe wicked People, that mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſlaundered her good Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in Chriſt; that thoſe who would not be bettered by her unblamable Life, might be hardned by her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable Death.</p>
               <p>But this we may account God's <hi>ſtrange</hi> Work, moſt commonly the way of Holineſs doth end more comfortably. And we are aſſured the upright ones end is peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37. though we cannot be ſure of peace in his Soul juſt before his End; becauſe we read God's Judgments are unſearchable, and his ways paſt finding out. Thus of the firſt Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Second is this, [That to be followed much with Satan's ſoreſt Temptations is no ill Sign] St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf complained of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours within, as well as Troubles without. Yea Chriſt himſelf, when
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:179751:99"/>his Heavenly Father had ſolemnly owned him for his Beloved Son in whom he was well pleaſed, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.17. the next news we hear of him was, that he was led into the Wilderneſs to be tempted of the Devil, (yea 40 days, as St. <hi>Mark</hi> hath it. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.11.13.) whilſt the ſtrong man armed keepeth poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the things he hath are in peace. The Pyrate ſpendeth not his biggeſt Bullet upon the empty Ships, but upon the laden, and beſt laden. So Satan doth not caſt the fiery Darts of his Temptations, againſt thoſe that are under his accurſed ſlavery, and follow the ways he would have them, (at leaſt not uſually, nor unleſs he have them at a pinch, as we ſay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome conſiderable Croſſes as to the World,) but rather againſt thoſe that have choſen a better Maſter, and turned through grace into the Holy Path.</p>
               <p>The third Aſſertion in anſwer to
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:179751:99"/>the ſaid Objection is thus, [That a Chriſtian's Fear of Dying uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, is no ſign that he ſhall Dye ſo.] As God bids his Prophet, ſay to them that are of a fearfull heart, <hi>Be ſtrong and fear not:</hi> So he is pleaſed many times to ſtrengthen and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them abundantly, and do for them above all they could ask or think. He that had his Spirit overwhelmed in him, and walked mournfully all the year round by reaſon of thoſe blaſphemous Suggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the unclean Spirit had ſo conſtantly exerciſed him with, yet at length was enabled to offer up joyfull Praiſes to his God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ended his days in a bleſſed peace, (as a great Authour hath teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.) The like is recorded of Mr. <hi>Saunders,</hi> viz. That though he was ſometimes much concerned (as we call it) to think what he ſhould do if he ſhould be brought to the fiery Trial, yet when he was brought to
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:179751:100"/>it, he had his Fears removed, and (being ſtrengthened with God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Might) paſſed as comfortably through that Sea of Blood, as the reſt of that noble Army of Martyrs.</p>
               <p>The fourth Aſſertion. [God often worketh by contraries, and brings about his gracious purpoſes by means that ſeem the moſt unlikely.] As he brought water for his People, not out of the Sea or the River, but out of the Rock; ſo he often ſuffers thoſe People to be moſt ſhaken with Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, whom he meaneth moſt to eſtabliſh, to make moſt grounded and rooted in the Faith. Of which I might inſtance in <hi>Luther</hi> and others, if it were my purpoſe to enlarge on this particular.</p>
               <p>The fifth Aſſertion. [The Arm of God's Love is infinitely ſtronger than the Arm of a Chriſtian's Faith:] If therefore he be ſuch in ſincerity, he may be ſure that either he ſhall not Dye in deſpair (or Diſcomfort) or
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:179751:100"/>elſe that he ſhall not be ruined by Dying ſo. For if his Graces be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much oppoſed, yet God's Kindneſs to his Servants is abſolute and unconquerable. If their Faith and Hope ſhould ſeem to be ſhaken beyond recovery, yet compaſſion cannot fail in the Father of Mercies, and his Covenant of Peace ſhall not be removed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.10. ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>What ſhall ſeparate us</hi> (ſo ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the reſt of the faithfull as of himſelf) <hi>from the Love of Chriſt? Neither Death nor Life, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come;</hi> (that is, they ſhall never do it, by any means, or any ſad <hi>Circumſtances</hi> that can attend them.)</p>
               <p>The ſixth Aſſertion [Deſpair, in all kinds and caſes, is no ſuch heinous and dangerous Sin as ſome have ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.] (And it were to be wiſhed that ſome Authours, otherwiſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and good, had written more cautiouſly about it than they have
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:179751:101"/>done.) And thoſe that deſpaired of <hi>Francis Spira</hi>'s Salvation, becauſe he ended his days in the darkneſs of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair may ſeem as unskilfull, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable: and I believe they have been blamed for it by many Divines beſides, and ſince, Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi> — But to come directly to the point it ſelf. <hi>Deſpair</hi> therefore may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in ſeveral ſorts of People, and on ſeveral grounds (or occaſions of it.)</p>
               <p>As to the firſt; <hi>Deſpair</hi> in a wicked man, if total and ordinary, I confeſs muſt needs be a very ſad matter; becauſe it hinders him from uſing the means of Salvation. Yet it doth not make his Salvation impoſſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis not impoſſible for it to be removed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To deſpair of Salvation out of a conceit, that there is not in Chriſt a ſufficient Power and Merit for that purpoſe: This, I ſay, is no leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; becauſe it is grounded on a
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:179751:101"/>prevalent Unbelief, and argues the Perſon under it to have no right Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Perſon of Chriſt, or the Excellency and Alſufficiency of his Merit and Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But for a true Chriſtian to be brought into Deſpair by <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes,</hi> this I cannot conceive to be ſuch a heinous Sin, or ſuch a dangerous Caſe. For example; If through Melancholy, or Satan's Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, he be brought to think, that he is under the guilt of the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Sin, then he cannot chuſe but deſpair of being pardoned. And though I believe it is a great truth, that no true Chriſtian ſhall ever be guilty of the unpardonable Sin (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an intereſt in Chriſt, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt, even ſuch as walk not after the Fleſh but after the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, 2. and for other reaſons that need not now be named:) Yet I doubt not but ſuch a one may fear
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:179751:102"/>he is under it, and verily think ſo: I remember Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> tells us it was the caſe of Mr. <hi>John Glover</hi> a Perſon of exemplary Piety. So that Deſpair, in ſuch perſons and on ſuch grounds, may be reckoned amongſt thoſe Frailties and Infirmities which our God doth pardon of courſe to his adopted Children in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>He is (what he is ſtiled) their <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father,</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.) and we can eaſily underſtand that the Child is incomparably ſafer by his Father's Hold of him, than by any Hold that he can take of his Father.</p>
               <p>He is their God for ever, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 48.14. and no Darkneſs or Diſcomfort, no Terrour of Life or ſhadow of Death ſhall ever deprive them of their Intereſt in him, or diſanull his purpoſe of Grace which was towards them in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> before the World began.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 6. But after all this, you may perhaps (when your turn comes) be
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:179751:102"/>as much afraid to Dye as others are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very like ſo; I can ſay nothing to the contrary: nor can I tell in the leaſt how it will be with me, in point of comfort at my laſt Hour. I well know, that of my ſelf I am as nothing, and all my Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency is of God. I ſhall therefore fear the laſt Enemy, either much or little, or not at all, according as that King Eternal ſhall be pleaſed to grant or to withhold the Influences and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances of his Holy Spirit. If he ſhould leave me to my ſelf, to the Power of Temptation (to the Doubts and Sins of my own Heart) I know my Spirit would fail on a ſuddain, and I ſhould look like thoſe that have been ſeven Days dead. But (good Reader) how weak ſoever, I or others may be, yet our God is Strong and Faithfull and True: and the Empyrean Heaven may ſooner fall and periſh, than the leaſt part of his promiſed Goodneſs fail. Go on
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:179751:103"/>therefore, O Chriſtian, in the <hi>good Way</hi> with a good Courage and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; Live upon Chriſt, and live unto him, and ſerve that bleſſed Lord with Joyfulneſs of Heart; Fear not the Reproach of Men, nor be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of their Revilings: Endeavour to bring Glory to the Name of Chriſt by walking (more and more) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes his Goſpel, and then never value a thouſand hard Cenſures, and diſgracefull Names, or any other cruel Arts that Hell can invent to diſcourage Religion by. For e're long through the tender Mercies of our God, thou ſhalt be above the reach of all thy Enemies; when thou removeſt from the beſt of thy Friends on Earth, thou ſhalt dwell with thoſe that Love thee better; When thy Soul ſhall leave this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant World, it ſhall ſee the Love of the Lord Jeſus; that free, that full, that glorious Love which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:179751:103"/>than Life and ſtronger than Death, which makes the Hoſt of Heaven glad, and fills the Seraphins with Sacred Joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>A POSTSCRIPT, <hi>Attempting the Reſolution of a weighty Queſtion; with an Appendix to the</hi> 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Section concerning Chriſt's Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, in a Letter to a Learned Authour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIR, I am ſatisfied in your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Neceſſity, or at leaſt the Expediency of Anſwering thoſe Oppoſers, who enquire how 'tis likely the Soul can <hi>Act,</hi> when 'tis without its <hi>Body</hi> to act in? ſince it apparently dependeth on the Body in its Operations, and its actings are evidently hindered when the Body is indiſpoſed by Sleep or Sickneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:179751:104"/>Which I hope may in part be ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the enſuing Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Soul's depending on the Body in ſome of its Actings doth only prove, that it hath need of the Body in it's <hi>preſent State</hi> wherein it was appointed to act in it, and by it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Soul doth act in ſome ways very much, when the Body leaſt contributes to its Operation. Even in Sleep it ſelf the Soul is not wholly unactive, for it then acteth by Thoughts and Dreams.</p>
               <p>And as ſome tell us they ſeldom wake but out of ſome Degree of Dreaming: So 'tis impoſſible for any to prove that they did not <hi>dream,</hi> or exerciſe a <hi>thinking</hi> power in their deepeſt Sleeps; for that may be, though they do not remember it. Some Mens Fancies and Conſciences have acted moſt ſtrangely, when their Bodies have lain as dead many Hours together; declaring when they came to their Senſes, what a
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:179751:104"/>ſad caſe they had been in, and thought themſelves to have been in Hell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That its Dependance on the Body in ſome of its Operations, doth not prove its Dependance on it in All: or in thoſe that are moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to it, as <hi>Underſtanding</hi> and <hi>Willing, Hoping</hi> or <hi>Fearing, Joying</hi> or <hi>Sorrowing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That God who hath told us in his word that it is Immortal, and cannot be Killed (<hi>Math.</hi> 10.28.) doth know how to preſerve its operating power, without the help of a Weak and Dying Body. If its Life and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth not depend upon its union with the Body, why ſhould we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive its Operation and Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to depend on it?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Though the Soul in its <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be without its Terreſtrial Body, yet it may not therefore be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have <hi>No</hi> Body to <hi>Act</hi> in: for it may have an <hi>Aërial Body;</hi> which was ſo far from being counted ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:179751:105"/>by the Ancients, that they did ſuppoſe the Angels themſelves to be (in ſome ſenſe) embodied Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And perhaps it may be hard to prove, that the Holy Apoſtle doth not mean ſome ſuch thing, when he ſaith [<hi>we deſire to be cloathed upon, with our Houſe which is from Heaven,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.2. and (verſe 4.) <hi>not that we would be uncloathed, but cloathed upon.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="6">6. When the ſame Apoſtle had (in his Rapture to the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) ſuch Divine Diſcoveries as he could not utter, he aſſures us, that he could not tell us in what State he had them. <hi>[Whether in the Body or out of the Body, I cannot tell]</hi> 2 Cor. 12.2, 3. Which it ſeems was very remarkable, ſince it is mentioned twice in thoſe verſes. Now how can it be imagined, that the Apoſtle ſhould make it his buſineſs, to declare that he knew not whether he had thoſe Revelations <hi>in</hi> the Body or
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:179751:105"/>
                  <hi>out</hi> of it, if the Soul without its Terreſtrial Body, were an Unactive and Inſenſible thing?</p>
               <p>Sir, I have alſo conſidered farther about the great Point we were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of; [whether Chriſt be the Son of God on the Account of his miraculous Conception?] and for the Negative I would humbly offer theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Affirmative ſeems to enervate the Arguments, that Orthodox Divines uſe to prove him the Son of God by Real and Eternal Generation; or at leaſt, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the neceſſity of arguing about it: For (they will ſay) what need any Man ſeek ſuch a ground of his Sonſhip, if he may fitly be called the Son of God upon a far different Account?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe Chriſt is not <hi>therefore</hi> called [the Son of God] in any Scripture unleſs it be in <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. And I think it hath not yet been
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:179751:106"/>proved that he is ſo called in that place on that Account, for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the only Nerve that the proof of the contrary-minded is faſtened on; which methinks ſhould afford no cogent Argument: For the Particle [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] may be conſequential as well as cauſal: And 'tis hard to find any thing in that Text (or context) that will prove it to be <hi>cauſal.</hi> And poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly the Conjunctive [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] may make againſt it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Relationes ſe mutuò ponunt:</hi> If therefore Chriſt be the Son of God upon ſeveral grounds, he muſt have ſeveral Filiations in <hi>Reſpect of God,</hi> and ſo ſhould be <hi>more</hi> than <hi>one Son</hi> of God; unleſs a Man ſuppoſe his miraculous Conception to be the <hi>only</hi> Reaſon why he is called the Son of God; which as it will never be granted by the Orthodox, ſo I think it is not aſſerted by any at all.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It ſeems needleſs for Chriſt to have any other Filiation in Reſpect
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:179751:106"/>of God, than what is grounded on Eternal Generation. As to himſelf 'tis plain he hath no need: And there ſeems to be as little need of it as to us; Becauſe his Eternal Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is every way ſufficient to eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the <hi>Humane</hi> Nature, and to put a glorious Value upon what he did and ſuffered for us.</p>
               <p>I have not conſulted Authours upon this Occaſion: So that this is but the Reſult of my own Thoughts, which may have need of Rectifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the whole, Sir, is humbly ſubmitted to your favourable, yet impartial Cenſure, by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Obliged Servant, <hi>J. B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>A Dialogue between a</hi> Paſtor <hi>and</hi> Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner, <hi>touching the</hi> Lord's Supper <hi>Wherein the moſt material Doubts and Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, about Receiving that Holy</hi> Sacrament, <hi>are removed, and the Way thereto diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be both Plain and Pleaſant. Very uſefull for private Chriſtians in theſe Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Times. With ſome ſhort Prayers, fitted for that Occaſion; and a Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayer, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Private Families By</hi> Michael Altham, <hi>Vicar of</hi> Latton <hi>in</hi> Eſſex <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſt for the Heavy-Laden. Promiſed by our only Lord and Saviour</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>to all Sincere Believers, Practically diſcourſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By</hi> Clement Elis <hi>Rector of</hi> Kirkby <hi>in</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamſhire. <hi>Author of the</hi> Gentile Sinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some Queries to Proteſtants</hi> Anſwered. <hi>And an Explanation of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick's</hi> Belief <hi>in Four Great Points conſidered.</hi> 1. <hi>Concerning their</hi> Church. 2. <hi>Their</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. 3. Juſtification. 4. Civil Government.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 56, Line 20, for <hi>greateſt,</hi> reade <hi>groſſeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179751:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
